<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://www.gutenberg.org/tei/marcello/0.4/dtd/pgtei.dtd" [

<!ENTITY u5  "http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/">

]>

<TEI.2 lang="en">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>An Essay on the Antient and Modern State of Ireland</title>
      <author><name reg="Brooke, Henry">Henry Brooke</name></author>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition n="1">Edition 1</edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
      <date>November 10, 2008</date>
      <idno type="etext-no">27226</idno>
      <availability>
        <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and
        with almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it
        away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg
        License online at www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>
        Created electronically.
      </bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language id="en"></language>
      <language id="la"></language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change>
      <date value="2008-11-10">November 10, 2008</date>
      <respStmt>
        <name>
            Produced by Robert Cicconetti, David King, and the Online
            Distributed Proofreading Team at &lt;http://www.pgdp.net/&gt;.
        </name>
      </respStmt>
      <item>Project Gutenberg TEI edition 1</item>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<pgExtensions>
  <pgStyleSheet>
    .boxed           { x-class: boxed }
    .shaded          { x-class: shaded }
    .rules           { x-class: rules; rules: all }
    .indent          { margin-left: 2 }
    .bold            { font-weight: bold }
    .italic          { font-style: italic }
    .smallcaps       { font-variant: small-caps }
    .gesperrt        { font-style: italic }
  </pgStyleSheet>

  <pgCharMap formats="txt.iso-8859-1">
    <char id="U0x2014">
      <charName>mdash</charName>
      <desc>EM DASH</desc>
      <mapping>--</mapping>
    </char>
    <char id="U0x2003">
      <charName>emsp</charName>
      <desc>EM SPACE</desc>
      <mapping>  </mapping>
    </char>
    <char id="U0x2026">
      <charName>hellip</charName>
      <desc>HORIZONTAL ELLIPSIS</desc>
      <mapping>...</mapping>
    </char>
  </pgCharMap>
</pgExtensions>

<text lang="en">
  <front>
    <div>
      <divGen type="pgheader" />
    </div>
    <div>
      <divGen type="encodingDesc" />
    </div>

    <div rend="page-break-before: always">
      <p rend="font-size: xx-large; text-align: center">An Essay On The</p>
      <p rend="font-size: xx-large; text-align: center">Ancient and Modern State</p>
      <p rend="font-size: xx-large; text-align: center">Of Ireland</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">With the Various Important Advantages</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">Thereunto Derived,</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">under the auspicious Reign of His most sacred Majesty</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">King GEORGE the Second.</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">Including a particular Account</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">of the great and glorious</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">St. Patrick</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">By</p>
      <p rend="font-size: x-large; text-align: center">Henry Brooke</p>
      <p rend="text-align: center">Dublin: Printed</p>
      <p rend="text-align: center">London: Re-Printed</p>
      <p rend="text-align: center">for R. Griffiths.</p>
      <p rend="text-align: center">MDCCLX.</p>
    </div>
    <div rend="page-break-before: always">
      <head>Contents</head>
      <divGen type="toc" />
    </div>
  </front>
<body>

<pb n='003'/><anchor id='Pg003'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>Dedication.</head>

<p>
TO
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Matthew M<hi rend="vertical-align: super">c</hi>. Namara</hi>,
</p>

<p>
Of <hi rend='italic'>LIMERICK</hi>, Esq;
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Counsellor</hi> at LAW.
</p>

<p>
Justly sensible, Sir, how
sincerely You have the Character
and Esteem of our Native
Country at Heart, I take Leave
to offer to Your Perusal, and
commend to Your favourable Acceptance,
the following Sheets.
</p>

<p>
What gave them Rise, was my happening,
some Time since, to have fallen into
Company with two or three sprightly young
Gentlemen, then just returned from their
Continental Rambles,&mdash;who&mdash;altho' little
burthened with the Religion, Laws, Learning,
Policy, Customs, Habits, Manners, or
Languages of any, or the several Countries
they had scampered thro', affected, nevertheless,
an high Contempt for this,&mdash;their
Native.
</p>

<pb n='004'/><anchor id='Pg004'/>

<p>
I listened with silent Indignation, and
determined to contribute my Mite towards
giving such unattentive, uninformed
Youths, a more adequate Idea of this Kingdom,
under its ancient and under its present
happy Establishment.
</p>

<p>
The common Accidents of Time must
lead them by better Authority to clearer
Knowledge: In the mean while, I profess
my Obligations to them, as they have given
me this Opportunity of declaring my Regard
to my Country in general, and the
particular Attachments that ever bind me,
in the strictest Sense of Fidelity and Esteem,
to a Friend so worthy as You have
been to,
</p>

<p>
Sir,<lb/>
Your very obliged, and<lb/>
Most obedient Servant.
</p>

</div>

<pb n='005'/><anchor id='Pg005'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>Essay.</head>

<p>
In a Nation, where almost every
Gentleman is better acquainted, and
more conversant, with the Nature
and Circumstances of other Countries
than those of his own, the
Publication of such Hints as may somewhat
contribute to remove so odd an Inattention, and
induce those far better qualified to render a Subject
so interesting some Justice, will not, I
hope, be deemed an Impertinence; in one especially
who, by this Essay, however feeble, hath
nothing beside the Honour and Advantage of
<pb n='006'/><anchor id='Pg006'/>
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> in View, a Kingdom whereof he is, without
Vanity, proud of being a Native.
</p>

<p>
As the Story of Savages and Barbarians can
contain nothing instructive, or entertaining, the
<hi rend='italic'>Antemilesian</hi> Inhabitants of this Land having
been mostly such, and all surviving Accounts
of them almost totally overcast with Fable, we
are therefore, in treating of the antient <hi rend='italic'>Scotia</hi>, or
modern <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, to refer principally to three
distinguished æras, whereof the <emph>first</emph> is, its
being peopled by an <hi rend='italic'>Iberian</hi> or <hi rend='italic'>Spanish</hi>
Colony: The <emph>second</emph>, truly glorious, the Arrival of St.
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>, in his most salutary Mission: The <emph>third</emph>
and last, its Cession to <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Second, King
of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, (the first of the Royal Race of
<hi rend='italic'>Plantagenet</hi>) partly from a pretended Title of
<hi rend='italic'>Adrian</hi> the Fourth, Pope of <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>; partly
from the restless and insatiable Desires of <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi>;
<emph>more</emph> from the manifold Infirmities of the then reigning
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Chiefs&mdash;but above all, from the peculiarly
adverse Fate of <hi rend='italic'>Roderick</hi>, the last of our
Kings.
</p>

<p>
The assiduous, exact, and candid Author of the
<hi rend='italic'>Dissertations</hi>,<note place='foot'><hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>,
1753, <hi rend='italic'>M. Reilly</hi>, Editor.</note> lately published, on the Origin,
Government, Letters, Sciences, Religion,
Manners and Customs of the antient Inhabitants
of this Country, hath put all those Matters in
so clear and happy, and, at the same Time, in so
strong a Light, by the Powers of various foreign
Testimonies, of undeniable Authenticity,
coincident with our own, that scarce any Thing
new can be offered on the same Subject.
</p>

<p>
It may, however, in general be observed,
that <hi rend='italic'>Milesius</hi>, a <hi rend='italic'>Spanish</hi> Prince, so far
back as the Reign of <hi rend='italic'>Solomon</hi> (instigated by Necessity,
or induced by Ambition) with a considerable
<pb n='007'/><anchor id='Pg007'/>
Number of Associates and Followers,
landed from the Western Parts of <hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi>, on the
Southern Coasts of this Island, where it is probable
they met little, or but faint Opposition,
from wild and undisciplined Inhabitants.
</p>

<p>
Those People, from their early Knowledge
of the <hi rend='italic'>Phœnician</hi> Arts and Letters, imported
such Rudiments of Government and Learning,
as those primitive Times admitted; a Truth
visible from the Similarity or rather Identity of
the <hi rend='italic'>Phœnician</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Scotic</hi> Alphabet.
</p>

<p>
This antient Colony quietly settled here, remote
from the Storms and Revolutions of the
greater World, and secured by Situation from
its hostile Incursions, there is no Doubt but the
Cultivation of Religion, Philosophy, Politicks,
Poetry, and Musick, became the chief Objects
of popular Study and Application: The Spirit
of Ambition in succeeding Ages, with its unhappy
concomitant Train of Sedition, Faction,
and Violence, the foreign Invasions, and often
the intestine Oppressions and Calamities, to
which our neighbouring Nations were subject,
calling forth the protective or conciliating Aids
of those ancient Heroes, made them great Masters
also in the Art military.
</p>

<p>
The Pentarchy originally formed by those
<hi rend='italic'>Iberian</hi> or <hi rend='italic'>Celtic Spaniards</hi>, with a
popular Right of Election, was certainly a Kind of Government
extremely consistent with the Essence and
Genius of true Liberty, and a System derived
from the Patriarchs themselves. For when the
various Necessities of Society required a Subordination,
together with some stated Maxims to
go by, to avoid the confused and promiscuous
Intercourse in a State of Nature; then did the
People elect the most Virtuous and Wise, to lead
<pb n='008'/><anchor id='Pg008'/>
and conduct them in Times of War and Trouble;
to govern, inform, and protect them, in
milder and more auspicious Seasons. Then was
the Motto of the Crown, or of the chief Ensign
of Pre-eminence, <hi rend='italic'>Digniori detur</hi>, and so continued
till the Degeneracy of Time, and the
baneful Growth of Avarice and Pride, with the
feverish Lust of Power, perverted it to&mdash;<hi rend='italic'>Rapiat
Fortior</hi>!
</p>

<p>
Such, thro' a long Succession of Ages, was
the Condition, and such at length the Fate of
this Kingdom, destroyed after a longer Continuance
than any other can boast, by the Abuse
of its own Powers; a sure Argument that all
created Beings, all sublunary Institutions, however
wisely composed, in the very Essence of
their Creation, and in the very Rudiments of
their Formation, comprehend, at the same Time,
the Seeds of Dissolution: Yet it is not more remarkable
than true, that in the most boisterous
Periods of this Kingdom's antient Establishment,
the Arts and Sciences, with the fundamental
Principles of Constitution, were preserved
and cherished with inviolable Assiduity.
The Priests, Philosophers, Advocates, Annalists,
Poets and Musicians, were obliged to preserve
Religion, political Wisdom, Law, History, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi>
hereditarily in their respective Tribes, and to
educate in these different Branches the Chiefs
and Nobles of the Land, for which they were
graciously maintained in secure and splendid
Tranquillity: Those Sages attended the National
Conventions, where all publick Acts were religiously
recorded, and all Abuses of Power and
Government retrenched or reformed; nor were
they permitted, except in Case of extraordinary
Necessity, or uncommon Merit, to deviate from
<pb n='009'/><anchor id='Pg009'/>
their proper and primitive Spheres of Action:
Since, where an harmonious Subordination of
Rank and Order hath not been duly preserved,
even in free Estates, Liberty itself (wisely attempered,
the greatest of all social Blessings)
hath often, from Abuse and Neglect, sickened
into Licentiousness, the immediate lewd Mother
of Anarchy! In the visible Creation, the direct
Result of infinite Wisdom, the lesser Planets do
not interfere with, much less shock or oppose
the Motions and Revolutions of the greater;
they constantly keep the Distances first prescribed
them, and all move regularly to their
respective Ends. The most verdant and fragrant
Meadows may, from the too frequent Irruption
of muddy Waters, degenerate into
noxious Marshes, if some Care was not taken
to divert those impure Gushings into their proper
Channels. Hence it may be inferred, that
laying open the most honorary, as well as important
and useful Professions of Society, to the
Intrusion, or rather pyratical Invasions, of the
Scum and Dregs of the People, cannot, however
varnished over with the fictitious Colourings
of pretended Liberty, consist with true Political
Wisdom.
</p>

<p>
Those ancient <hi rend='italic'>Sophi</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Literati</hi> enjoyed
their Places with the greater Security, that they
were uninvadable by the inferior Classes of Mankind;
with the greater Content and Chearfulness,
that much Esteem and Emolument were
connected with them: The Priest and Advocate
informed and directed the Conscience and Conduct;
the Historian and Annalist recorded the
Institutions; the Poet and Musician celebrated
and sung the Exploits of their Kings and Leaders:
No Wonder then this Kingdom should
<pb n='010'/><anchor id='Pg010'/>
have been revered at Home, and admired Abroad;
when Religion formed, Erudition nurtured,
Philosophy strengthened, History preserved,
Rhetorick adorned, Musick softened,
and Poesy refined, the National Wisdom and
Accomplishments; to all which was added, a
thorough Knowledge of Tactics, and great
Skill and Agility in all the athletick Arts, and
bodily Exercises.
</p>

<p>
In the Versions of some original Codes exported
by our Countryman, the learned and
pious St. <hi rend='italic'>Fiechry</hi>, still extant in the
<hi rend='italic'>Navarre</hi> Library at <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, the
Constitutional Wisdom of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> appears in a clear and happy
Light: Persons, Things, Actions, and Expressions,
were cautiously attended to, by the Laws; <emph>Persons</emph>,
in their Minority, Youth, and Manhood,
according to their different Ranks in the State,
so as by Care, Education, and Discipline, to
render them, some subservient, others useful,
some beneficial, and others ornamental thereunto.
<emph>Things</emph>, so carefully, as to prevent, by
prohibatory Laws, Wastes of whatsoever Kind,
and to ascertain to each Individual, as well as
Society, their proper and distinct Rights. <emph>Actions</emph>,
by directing those in general, and particular,
to the Honour of the Deity and Welfare
of the Community: <emph>Expression</emph>, by the penal
Interdiction of prophane Cursing and Swearing,
Obscenity, Scurrility, Calumny, and Detraction,
yet with a full Indulgence of proper Satire
against such as merited popular Reprehension,
or Contempt; the Satirist's Pen in those
Days being as much dreaded, or rather more
so, than the Magistrate's Rod, and consequently
as diligently avoided by a Demeanour absolutely
irreproachable.
</p>

<pb n='011'/><anchor id='Pg011'/>

<p>
It appeareth that, under the antient Government
of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, the Education of the landed
Gentry, when Luxury, with its wasteful Catalogue
of Vices, had not rendered Property so
mutable and wavering as in modern Ages,
was provided for; whether by the immediate
Care of Parents, or essential Attention of Guardians,
by the Laws of the Land; in order that
Gentlemen should, to the Antiquity of Birth
and Possession, add the important Dignity of
Learning, and social Refinement of Arts: Since
a Man at the Head of an original Estate, who
should want the necessary Cultivation of Letters,
was considered only as a Peasant in Disguise,
and not more respected than a Hewer of
Wood, or Drawer of Water.
</p>

<p>
In these Writings of St. <hi rend='italic'>Fiechry</hi>, the legislative
Wisdom of <hi rend='italic'>Olam-Fodla</hi>; the philosophically-religious
Capacity of <hi rend='italic'>Cormac-O Quin</hi>, who,
from the pure Light of Nature, in a great Measure
defeated the absurd <hi rend='italic'>Polytheism</hi> of the
<hi rend='italic'>Druids</hi>; the consummate Integrity and Impartiality of
<hi rend='italic'>Federach</hi> the Just, and <hi rend='italic'>Moran</hi> his Chief
Justice; the Magnanimity of <hi rend='italic'>Con-Ked-Cathagh</hi>; the Conquests
of <hi rend='italic'>Kineth Mac Alpin</hi>; the long, glorious,
and peaceful Reign of <hi rend='italic'>Conary</hi> the Great,
<hi rend='italic'>coæval</hi> with the Birth of our Blessed Lord and
Saviour <hi rend='italic'>Jesus Christ</hi>, (undoubtedly the happiest,
brightest, and most blissful Period the World
ever saw;) are all displayed in a copious masterly
Style, yet with strict chronological Exactness.
</p>

<p>
This learned St. <hi rend='italic'>Fiechry</hi> was Founder of the
University in <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, in the Beginning of the
8th Century. The better to enable him to carry
on that noble Work, he obtained of <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the
Great a Tax on all Wheel-Carriages, within
<pb n='012'/><anchor id='Pg012'/>
the Barriers of that City: Whence, a Hackney-Coach
is at this Day technically term'd <hi rend='italic'>Fiacre</hi>.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the Great, in order to repair the cruel
and truly lamentable literary Dilapidations of
the ferocious North-men, invited Numbers of
the learned and pious <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> to the Continent,
where he established and entertained them with
Dignity, Tenderness, and Respect. In a curious
Manuscript of <hi rend='italic'>Nicholaus Gurtlerus</hi>, (now
in the <hi rend='italic'>French</hi> King's <hi rend='italic'>Parisian</hi> Library)
Author of the <hi rend='italic'>Origines Mundi</hi>, where he alludes to these
Times, you find the following favourable, but true Account of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.&mdash;<foreign lang="la"
rend="font-style: italic">Temporibus illis, barbaris
Normannorum Cohortibus undequaque irrumpentibus,
Religio, Fides, Philosophia, Virtus, Hospitalitas,
Fortitudo, Castitas, necnon et Amœniores
omnium generum Artes, Hibernia solummodò natali,
veluti Solo, viguerunt</foreign>; little Wonder that
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> should have been esteemed the
<hi rend='italic'>Ierne</hi>, or sacred Isle of the <hi rend='italic'>Greeks</hi>, the
<hi rend='italic'>Insula Sanctorum</hi>, or Island of Saints of the
<hi rend='italic'>Romans</hi>.&mdash;Would to
Heaven our Countrymen had, upon all considerable
Occasions, recollected those deserved Encomiums,
thereby to approve them worthy their
applauded Origin, and native Soil!
</p>

<p>
We now proceed to consider <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> in her
happiest and brightest View, after the Admission
and Propagation of Christianity. It is certain
there were many Christians in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, before
the Arrival of <hi rend='italic'>Palladius</hi> in 431, or of St.
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> the Year following: St. <hi rend='italic'>Kieran</hi>,
St. <hi rend='italic'>Ailbe</hi>, St. <hi rend='italic'>Declan</hi>, and St.
<hi rend='italic'>Ibar</hi>, whom <hi rend='italic'>Ussher</hi> calls the
Precursors, or Forerunners of St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>, are
pregnant Proofs of this; they were of the Birth of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>,
from whence they travelled to <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>,
in Search of Education and Learning, where
<pb n='013'/><anchor id='Pg013'/>
they lived some Years, were ordained, and returned
Home about the Year 402.
</p>

<p>
It seems that those early Preachers confined
their Labours to particular Places, in which they
had considerable Success, but fell very short of
converting the Body of the Nation: However,
they sowed the Seed which St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> came
after to water: And it is certain that St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>
was so well satisfied with the Progress they
made, in their particular Districts in <hi rend='italic'>Munster</hi>,
that this was the last Province in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> he
thought proper to visit. That there were many
Christians in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, at this Period, seems to
be confirmed by <hi rend='italic'>Prosper</hi>, who, in giving an
Account of the Mission of <hi rend='italic'>Palladius</hi>, says, that
he was ordained by Pope <hi rend='italic'>Celestin</hi>, and sent the
first Bishop to the <hi rend='italic'>Scots</hi> believing in Christ.
This Passage can mean nothing else, but that
<hi rend='italic'>Palladius</hi>, born in Britain, was sent to the Scots
[i.e. the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>] who had already formed Churches
under <hi rend='italic'>Kieran</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Ailbe</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Declan</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Ibar</hi>; and so
the Bishop of St. <hi rend='italic'>Asaph</hi> expounds it. This then
was the next Attempt that was made for the Conversion of the
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>: <hi rend='italic'>Palladius</hi> engaged in a
more ample and extensive Design than his Predecessors,
yet he failed in the Execution of it,
stay'd but a short Time in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, and did little
worth remembring; he converted, however, a
few, and is said to have founded three Churches;
but he had neither Courage to withstand the
Fierceness of the heathen <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, nor Abilities,
for Want of the Language, proper for the
Work.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Nathi</hi>, the Son of <hi rend='italic'>Garcon</hi>, an
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Prince, opposed his preaching; upon which
<hi rend='italic'>Palladius</hi> left the Kingdom, and died in the Land of the
<hi rend='italic'>Picts</hi>, on the 15th of <hi rend='italic'>December</hi>, 431.
This
<pb n='014'/><anchor id='Pg014'/>
glorious Work was reserved for St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>, to
whose holy Life, divine Mission, and extraordinary
Success, I refer the Reader. This great
Apostle of the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> founded and built the Cathedral
Church of <hi rend='italic'>Ardmagh</hi>, about the Year
444, or 45, which, from that early Period to
this, hath continued the Metropolitan Church
of all <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>. So that 1194 Years passed away
from the Founding of the City of <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>, to that
of <hi rend='italic'>Ardmagh</hi>.
</p>

<p>
The various and most signal Blessings derived
to this Nation, from the salutary Mission of this
illustrious Saint, require, in Gratitude, our
giving the Reader yet a further Account of the
Author of such Happiness and Glory to <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<p>
He was born in the extreme Bounds of <hi rend='italic'>Britain</hi>,
(in that Part thereof which is now comprehended
within the Limits of the modern
<hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>) at a Village called <hi rend='italic'>Banaven</hi>,
in the Territory of <hi rend='italic'>Tabernia</hi>, (as he himself saith in
his Confession) in <hi rend='italic'>Vico Banaven Taberniæ</hi>, &amp;c.
He tells us that he was born of a good Family.
<foreign lang="la" rend="font-style:italic">Ingennuus fui secundum Carnem.</foreign>
His Father was <hi rend='italic'>Calphurnius</hi>, a Deacon, who was the Son
of <hi rend='italic'>Potitus</hi>, a Priest; from whence may be
clearly inferred that the Clergy were not restrained
from Matrimony in that Age. He was
just advanced into his sixteenth Year, when he
was taken Captive, the Manner of which is thus
related by St. <hi rend='italic'>Evin</hi> and others: His Father,
Mother, Brother, and five Sisters, undertook a
Voyage to <hi rend='italic'>Aremorick Gaul</hi>, (now called <hi rend='italic'>Bass
Bretagne</hi>) to visit the Relations of his Mother <hi rend='italic'>Couchessa</hi>.
It happened about this Time, that the
seven Sons of <hi rend='italic'>Factmude</hi>, a <hi rend='italic'>British</hi>
Prince, were banished, and took to the Sea; that, making
an Inroad into <hi rend='italic'>Aremorick Gaul</hi>, they took
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>
<pb n='015'/><anchor id='Pg015'/>
and his Sister, <hi rend='italic'>Lupita</hi>, (some say <hi rend='italic'>Tigrida</hi>
also) Prisoners. They brought their Captives to the North of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, and sold <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> to
<hi rend='italic'>Milcho Mac Huanan</hi>, a Prince of <hi rend='italic'>Dalaradia</hi>:
Others tell the Story in a different Manner, and
with a stronger Degree of Probability. That the <hi rend='italic'>Romans</hi>
having deserted <hi rend='italic'>Britain</hi>, to preserve
their own Country from the barbarous Incursions
of the <hi rend='italic'>Northern Hive</hi>, the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> made
frequent Conquests, in <hi rend='italic'>North Britain</hi> especially, whence
returning victorious, in one of those Expeditions
among others brought <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> Captive. But in
this they all agree, and he himself confirms it,
that he continued Prisoner in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> six Years;
he was sold to <hi rend='italic'>Milcho</hi> and his three Brothers,
which gave Occasion of his changing his Name into <hi rend='italic'>Cathraigh</hi>,
or rather <hi rend='italic'>Ceathir-Tigh</hi>, because
he served four Masters; <hi rend='italic'>Ceathir</hi> signifying four,
and <hi rend='italic'>Tigh</hi> a House or Family. <hi rend='italic'>Milcho</hi>
observing the Care and Diligence of his new Servant,
bought out the Shares of his Brothers, and made
him his own Property. He sent him to feed his Hogs on
<hi rend='italic'>Sliev-Mis</hi>. And St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> himself
tells us his Behaviour in this Office.
</p>

<p>
<q>My constant Business was to feed the Hogs.
I was frequent in Prayer; the Love and Fear
of God more and more inflamed my Heart;
my Faith was enlarged, and my Spirit augmented,
so that I said an hundred Prayers by
Day, and almost as many by Night. I arose
before Day to my Prayers, in the Snow, in the
Frost, and in the Rain, and yet I received no
Damage; nor was I affected with Slothfulness;
for then the Spirit of God was warm within
me.</q> It was here he perfected himself in the
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Language, the wonderful Providence of
God visibly appearing in this Instance of his
<pb n='016'/><anchor id='Pg016'/>
Captivity, that he should have the Opportunity
in his tender Years of becoming well acquainted
with the Language, Manners, and Dispositions
of that People, to whom he was intended as a
future Apostle. He continued six whole Years
in Servitude, and in the seventh was released.
There seems to have been a Law in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> for
this Purpose, agreeable to the Institution of
<hi rend='italic'>Moses</hi>, that a Servant should be released the
seventh Year.
</p>

<p>
Having parted from his Master, after a great
Variety of Distresses, he at length arrived to his
Parents, who received him with extraordinary
Joy; with these he remained two Years, and
probably would much longer, had he not by a
Vision been quickened to a more active and glorious
Life. In this he thought he saw a Man
coming to him from <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, whose Name was
<hi rend='italic'>Victoricus</hi>, with a great Number of Letters; that
he gave him one of them to read, in the Beginning
of which were contained these Words, <hi rend='italic'>Vox-Hiberionacum</hi>,
the Voice of the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>: While
he was reading this Letter, he thought the same
Moment, that he heard the Voice of the Inhabitants
who lived near the Wood of <hi rend='italic'>Foclut</hi>, in
the Barony of <hi rend='italic'>Tyr-Awley</hi>, and County of
<hi rend='italic'>Mayo</hi>, hard by the Western Sea, crying to him with an
audible and distinct Voice, <q>We intreat thee,
holy Youth, to come and walk among us.</q> He
was greatly amazed at this Vision, and awoke;
it animated him, however, to his future Studies
and heavenly Progress; so far even, that he
tells us himself, he thanked God, that after many
Years he had dealt with the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, according to
their crying out.
</p>

<p>
These early Scenes of this great Saint's Life,
should, among many others, serve as lessons of
<pb n='017'/><anchor id='Pg017'/>
Charity, Consideration, and Humility, to the
Rich, the Great, the Proud, and the Wanton;
who may recollect that, altho' he was well born,
he was nevertheless, in the most vigorous Season
of Life, a Slave and a Swine-Herd: Happy,
though wretched Servitude! In which, his leisure
Hours, mostly employed in Christian Confidence
and Prayer, made him so signally the
Favourite of Heaven, that from those cloudy
Dawnings, he in Process of Time became a
learned Doctor, a sanctified Missioner, a venerable
Prelate, an eminent Primate, a national Apostle,
and the bright Instructor of Kings! Such were
the fruitful Rewards of uninterrupted unshaken
Devotion, Piety, and Zeal! From this Time
he formed the steady Resolution of converting
the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>; and, the better to accomplish the heavenly
Task, he undertook a laborious Journey
to foreign Countries, to enrich his Mind with
Learning and Experience.
</p>

<p>
He continued abroad thirty-five Years, pursuing
his Studies under the Direction principally
of his Mother's Uncle, St. <hi rend='italic'>Martin</hi>, Bishop of
<hi rend='italic'>Tours</hi>, who had ordained him Deacon; and after
his Death, partly with St. <hi rend='italic'>German</hi>, Bishop of
<hi rend='italic'>Auxerre</hi>, (who ordained him a Priest, and called
his Name <hi rend='italic'>Magonius</hi>, which was the third Name
he was known by,) partly among a Colony of <hi rend='italic'>Hermits</hi> and
<hi rend='italic'>Monks</hi>, in some Islands of the <hi rend='italic'>Tuscan</hi>
Sea; and he employed a good Part of the
Time in the City of <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>, among the Canons
Regular of the <hi rend='italic'>Lateran</hi> Church: At length,
having his Soul thoroughly tempered with
religious Virtue, enlightened with the true
Evangelical Faith, and his Understanding enlarged
by the most profitable and edifying
Studies, he arrived in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> about the 60th
<pb n='018'/><anchor id='Pg018'/>
Year of his Age; and in the Year of our Lord
432, landed in the County of <hi rend='italic'>Wicklow</hi>, where
he began his Ministry, by the Conversion of
<hi rend='italic'>Sinel</hi>, a great Man in that Country, the Grandson
of <hi rend='italic'>Finchad</hi>, who ought to be remembered,
as he was the first Fruits of St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>'s Mission
in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>; he was the 8th in lineal Descent from
<hi rend='italic'>Cormac</hi>, King of <hi rend='italic'>Leinster</hi>, and came
afterwards to be enumerated among the Saints of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<p>
From this Country he sailed to an Island on
the Coast of the County of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>, called after
him <hi rend='italic'>Inis Phadring</hi>, and by the <hi rend='italic'>English</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Holm Patrick</hi> at this Day, where he and his faithful
Companions rested after their Fatigues. From
<hi rend='italic'>Inis Phadring</hi>, he sailed Northward to that Part
of <hi rend='italic'>Ulster</hi> called <hi rend='italic'>Ulidia</hi>, and put in at
<hi rend='italic'>Inbherslaying</hi> Bay. When he and his Fellow Labourers
landed, <hi rend='italic'>Dichu</hi>, the Son of <hi rend='italic'>Trichem</hi>, Lord
of the County, being informed that they were Pirates,
came out with armed Men in order to
kill them: But being struck with the venerable
Appearance of St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>, he gave him Audience,
and listened attentively to the Word of
Life preached by him; he changed his wicked
Purpose, believed, and was baptized, and brought
over all his Family to the Faith: It is further
observed of him, that he was the first Person in
<hi rend='italic'>Ulster</hi>, who embraced Christianity. He dedicated
the Land whereon his Conversion was
wrought to the Service of God, where a Church
was erected, changed after to an eminent Monastery.
He travelled hence by Land to <hi rend='italic'>Clunebois</hi>
in <hi rend='italic'>Dalaradia</hi>, to endeavour the Conversion
of his old Master <hi rend='italic'>Milcho</hi>, whose Service he had
left thirty-eight Years before; but this obstinate
Prince, hearing of the great Success of St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>'s
preaching, and ashamed to be persuaded
<pb n='019'/><anchor id='Pg019'/>
in his old Age, to forsake the Religion of his
Ancestors, (by one especially who had been his
Servant, in a most inferior Station,) made a
funeral Pile of his House and Goods, and by
the Instigation of the Enemy of Mankind,
burned himself therein: Thus ended <hi rend='italic'>Milcho McHuanan</hi>.
</p>

<p>
Hence St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> returned to <hi rend='italic'>Inis</hi>, the
Habitation of <hi rend='italic'>Dichu</hi>, and in his Journey converted
great Numbers to the true Faith of <hi rend='italic'>Christ</hi>.
In some time, he took his Leave of <hi rend='italic'>Dichu</hi>, and
bent his course Southward by Sea, keeping the
Coast on his Right-hand, and arrived at Port
<hi rend='italic'>Colbdi</hi>, where he landed, and committed the
Care of his Vessel to his Nephew <hi rend='italic'>Luman</hi>,
desiring him to wait for him there forty Days,
while he and his Disciples were travelling in the
inner Parts of the Country to preach the Gospel.
His Intention in this Journey was, to celebrate the Festival of
<hi rend='italic'>Easter</hi> in the Plains of <hi rend='italic'>Bregia</hi>, and
to be in the Neighbourhood of the Great Triennial
Convention at <hi rend='italic'>Tarah</hi>, which at this Season
was held by King <hi rend='italic'>Leogair</hi>, and all his Tributary Princes,
Nobles, <hi rend='italic'>Druids</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Annalists</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>and Fileas</hi>.
St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> wisely foreseeing that whatever Impressions
he should make on this august Assembly
must have an Influence on the whole Kingdom,
and therefore, being supported with invincible
Christian Fortitude, resolved not to be
absent from a Place where his Presence was so
conducive to the Ends of his Holy Ministry.
</p>

<p>
Never did the Spirit of popular Freedom
exert itself more powerfully or harmoniously,
than in those truly parliamentary Triennial Conventions
of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, where the supreme Monarch,
the Provincial Kings, the feudatory Lords,
the Nobles, landed Men, <hi rend='italic'>Druids</hi>, &amp;c. by the
<pb n='020'/><anchor id='Pg020'/>
unbiased Suffrages of the People, convened for
the Peace, good Government and Security of
each particular Province, as well as those of the
whole Kingdom. Many Centuries had this
wise Constitution subsisted here, before our
Neighbours, even of <hi rend='italic'>South Britain</hi>, knew any
thing relative to Houses, or Raiment; it being
notorious that so late as the Arrival of <hi rend='italic'>Julius
Cæsar</hi> among them, they painted their Bodies,
to render them terrible, and lived in the open
Fields. It is really somewhat surprzing that
People so near in Situation, should differ so
essentially in Disposition, as the Inhabitants of
those Islands have in all Ages; Hospitality having
been the distinguishing Attribute of the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, and it's
opposite Defect, that of the <hi rend='italic'>Britons</hi>;
the Account given of them by <hi rend='italic'>Horace</hi> 1700 and odd Years ago,
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Visam Britannes Hospitibus feros</foreign>,
being as literally applicable to them at this Day,
where the Force of Education doth not operate
to mitigate their natural Ferocity.
</p>

<p>
But to return: St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> in his Way to
<hi rend='italic'>Tarah</hi>, took up his Lodgings at the House of the
hospitable <hi rend='italic'>Sesgnen</hi> in <hi rend='italic'>Meath</hi>, who kindly
received and welcomed him. St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> preach'd Christ
and his Gospel to him; he believed, and was
baptized with his whole Family.
</p>

<p>
From the House of <hi rend='italic'>Sesgnen</hi>, he moved Westward,
and arrived on <hi rend='italic'>Easter Eve</hi> at
<hi rend='italic'>Fierta-fir-feic</hi>, on the Northern Banks of the River
<hi rend='italic'>Boyne</hi>, where he rested, resolving there to prepare for the next
Day's Solemnity. It was penal for any Person
at the Time of the Celebration of this solemn
Convention at <hi rend='italic'>Tarah</hi>, to kindle a Fire in the
Province, before the King's Bonfire first appeared.
I am of Opinion this was a religious Ceremony,
as the chief Deity of the ancient Inhabitants,
<pb n='021'/><anchor id='Pg021'/>
in exterior Worship especially, was <hi rend='italic'>Bel</hi>,
or <hi rend='italic'>Belus</hi>; whence <hi rend='italic'>Apollo</hi> or
<hi rend='italic'>Ap-haul</hi>, the Son of the Sun, whom they emblematically worshipped,
by those fiery Offerings; whence the first Day of
<hi rend='italic'>May</hi>, peculiarly dedicated to this <hi rend='italic'>Bel</hi>,
is even now in <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, called
<hi rend='italic'>Lha-Bel-Thinih</hi>, and probably from the same Source may be
derived the Custom of lighting up Bonfires, and Sops, on the
Eve of the 24th Day of <hi rend='italic'>June</hi>. St.
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> however, either not knowing or not minding this
Ceremony, lighted up a Fire before his Booth,
which altho' eight Miles distant from <hi rend='italic'>Tarah</hi>,
was very visible. It was seen with Astonishment
from Court, and the <hi rend='italic'>Druids</hi> informed the King,
that if he did not immediately extinguish the
Fire, he who kindled it, and his Successors,
should for ever hold the Principality of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>;
which hath hitherto turned out a true Prediction
of those Heathen Priests, in a Primatial and
Spiritual Principality.
</p>

<p>
The King dispatched Messengers to bring
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> before him, and gave his positive Orders,
that nobody should presume to rise out of his
Seat, or pay him the least Honour: But <hi rend='italic'>Ere</hi>,
the Son of <hi rend='italic'>Dego</hi>, ventured to disobey this Command;
he arose, and offered the Holy Father his
Seat. St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> preached to him and converted
him. He became a Person of eminent Sanctity,
and after some Time was consecrated by St.
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>, Bishop of <hi rend='italic'>Slain</hi>.
</p>

<p>
The Day following, when St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> and two
of his Disciples appeared unexpectedly at Court,
and preached to the King and his Nobles, <hi rend='italic'>Dubtach</hi>,
the King's Poet Laureat, payed Honour
and Respect to the Saint, and was converted
by his Preaching. <hi rend='italic'>Fiech</hi>, a young Poet, who
was under the Tuition of <hi rend='italic'>Dubtach</hi>, was also converted,
<pb n='022'/><anchor id='Pg022'/>
and afterwards made Bishop of <hi rend='italic'>Sletty</hi>,
and is said to have been the Author of a celebrated
Poem, composed in Praise of St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>.
<hi rend='italic'>Anselm</hi>, Arch-Bishop of <hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>,
relates the Conversion of <hi rend='italic'>Tingar</hi>, the Son of
<hi rend='italic'>Clito</hi>, (one of the Nobles in this Assembly,) in the same Manner.
The Queen also, and many others of the
Court, became Christians; and altho' the King
held out for a long Time with great Obstinacy,
yet at last he submitted to be baptized. St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi>
is said here to have wrought many Miracles:
There could not truly, even according to
the Purposes of human Wisdom, have happened
a more solemn or weighty Occasion, for God
Almighty's supporting this Holy Preacher by
Miracles, than when the collective Body of the
whole Nation was assembled together; from
whose Report and Conviction, the Influences of
his blessed Works and Doctrine must of Course
spread through the whole Kingdom.
</p>

<p>
His Conduct and Proceedings here, with a
particular Detail of the Miracles wrought by
him, may be had at large in the History of his
Life, published by <hi rend='italic'>John Colgan</hi>.
</p>

<p>
From <hi rend='italic'>Tarah</hi>, the Saint proceeded next to
<hi rend='italic'>Talten</hi>, not far from thence, at the Season of the
Royal Diversions: Here he preached to <hi rend='italic'>Cairbre</hi>,
and <hi rend='italic'>Conall</hi>, the two Brothers of King
<hi rend='italic'>Leogin</hi>; the former received him with great Indignity,
and perversely shut his Ears against his Doctrine;
but <hi rend='italic'>Conall</hi> believed, and was baptized, and gave
St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> a Place to build a Church on.
</p>

<p>
This <hi rend='italic'>Conall</hi> was Great-Grand-Father to
<hi rend='italic'>Columb-Kill</hi>. He spent the Remainder of this Year
in <hi rend='italic'>Meath</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Louth</hi>, and the Districts
adjoining, preaching, and converting great Numbers
of People. The <hi rend='italic'>Taltenian</hi> Sports above-mentioned,
<pb n='023'/><anchor id='Pg023'/>
have been much celebrated by the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>
Historians, and Antiquaries. They were a kind
of warlike Exercises, somewhat resembling the
<hi rend='italic'>Olympick</hi> Games, consisting of Racing, Tilts,
Tournaments, Wrestling, Leaping, Vaulting,
and all other manly and martial Exercises,
which gave Rise to the many hyperbolical
Tales, formerly related of those <hi rend='italic'>Taltenian</hi> Sports.
They were exhibited every Year at <hi rend='italic'>Talten</hi>, a
Mountain in <hi rend='italic'>Meath</hi>, for fifteen Days before,
and fifteen Days after the First of <hi rend='italic'>August</hi>. Their
first Institution is ascribed to <hi rend='italic'>Lughaid-lam-fadha</hi>,
the twelfth King of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, who began his
Reign <hi rend='italic'>A. M.</hi> 2764 (a sufficient Proof of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>'s Antiquity as a Kingdom). They were
ordained by <hi rend='italic'>Lughaid</hi>, in Gratitude to the Memory
of <hi rend='italic'>Tailte</hi>, the Daughter of <hi rend='italic'>Magh-More</hi>,
(a Prince of some Part of <hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi>) who having been married
to <hi rend='italic'>Eochaid</hi>, King of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, took the
same <hi rend='italic'>Lughaid</hi> under her Protection, and had the Care
of his Education in his Minority. From this
Princess both the Sports, and the Place where
they were celebrated, took their Names: From <hi rend='italic'>Lughaid</hi>, the
First of <hi rend='italic'>August</hi> was called <hi rend='italic'>Lugnasa</hi>,
or the Memory of <hi rend='italic'>Lughaid</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Nasa</hi> signifying
Memory, in the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Language.
</p>

<p>
In the Year of the World 2700, <hi rend='italic'>Gideon</hi> then
reigning fourth Judge of the <hi rend='italic'>Hebrews</hi>, appear'd
many Heroes, as <hi rend='italic'>Hercules</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Orpheus</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Castor</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Pollux</hi>,
the <hi rend='italic'>Argonauts</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Jason</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Laomedon</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Thesæus</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Dedalus</hi>, &amp;c. The <hi rend='italic'>Amazones</hi>,
Heroines of <hi rend='italic'>Scythic</hi>
Extraction, having lost their Husbands in
Battle, took up Arms themselves, with a manly
Spirit of Resentment, and (inspired with Love
of their deceased Husbands, and Grief for so
great and irretrievable a Loss!) subdued <hi rend='italic'>Asia</hi>,
and built <hi rend='italic'>Ephesus</hi>. <hi rend='italic'>Hercules</hi> and
<hi rend='italic'>Thesæus</hi> waged
<pb n='024'/><anchor id='Pg024'/>
War against those Heroines, and defeated them,
more to the Glory of the Vanquished than their
own, those Matrons having defended themselves
with surprizing Resolution. They cut off the
Guards set over them, and escaped the Severity
and Pride of their Conquerors. <hi rend='italic'>Hercules</hi>, in
Honour of such extraordinary heroick Females,
instituted the <hi rend='italic'>Olympick</hi> Games; as likewise did
<hi rend='italic'>Thesæus</hi>, the <hi rend='italic'>Isthmian</hi>, in the Year of
the World, about 2700, the <hi rend='italic'>Taltenian</hi> Sports, the very same
with the <hi rend='italic'>Olympick</hi>, brought sixty-four Years after
from <hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi> into <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, by
<hi rend='italic'>Tailte</hi>, and her Followers.
Now this <hi rend='italic'>Tailte</hi>, Queen of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, was
the Grand-daughter of an <hi rend='italic'>Amazone</hi> Princess,
those immortal Females having, with their Progeny,
Friends and Followers, to avoid the ruinous
Hostilities of <hi rend='italic'>Hercules</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Thesæus</hi>,
sought Shelter in <hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi>, whither they imported the
Learning of <hi rend='italic'>Trismegistus</hi>, the Grandson of
<hi rend='italic'>Mercury</hi>, and Glory of <hi rend='italic'>Ægypt</hi>, together
with all the literary Arts derived into <hi rend='italic'>Greece</hi>, from
<hi rend='italic'>Phœnicia</hi>, by <hi rend='italic'>Cadmus</hi>, the Brother
of <hi rend='italic'>Europa</hi>, about the Year of the World 2530,
<hi rend='italic'>Othoniel</hi> then reigning the first Judge of the
<hi rend='italic'>Hebrews</hi>. The Posterity of this ancient and illustrious Colony,
about the Year of the World 3000, (<hi rend='italic'>Solomon</hi> then
reigning with great Splendour, third King of
the <hi rend='italic'>Hebrews</hi>) settled in this Kingdom, as before
observed: So that, by an impartial Estimate of
Dates, Periods, and Facts, our Origin is well
ascertained, our early Possession of Letters, wise
Policy, and the politer Arts, proved, and the
Remark of an <hi rend='italic'>Italian</hi> Monk in the 7th Century,
from the University of <hi rend='italic'>Mongret</hi>, in an Epistle
to his Correspondent at <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>, justified,
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Nil mirum
Populum hunc Celtico Scythicum è præclarâ
Amazonidum stirpê oriundum, verâ Religionê et
<pb n='025'/><anchor id='Pg025'/>
incorruptâ Fide illuminatum, sapientia Doctrina
optimisque Morbidus ornatum, viros fortes et Fæminas
castas plerumque procreare</foreign>. A Rescript of
this Original Epistle still extant, in the <hi rend='italic'>Vatican</hi>
Library, some Years ago in the Hands of Father
Don <hi rend='italic'>Levy</hi>, may therefore, I believe, be
found in the College of <hi rend='italic'>Lombard</hi> at <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>.
</p>

<p>
In this shining Period were Cathedrals and
Churches erected, Universities founded and
established, Colleges, Seminaries and Schools
propagated in many Parts of this Kingdom,
which, at the same Time, became a peaceful
and hospitable Retreat to religious and learned
Men, disturbed on the Continent of <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>, by
the frequent Invasions, and cruel Hostilities of
the North-men, whose Piracies and Barbarity,
even <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> could not always escape! For,
from the Time of <hi rend='italic'>Artigrius</hi>, Archbishop of
<hi rend='italic'>Ardmagh</hi> in 822, for near 200 Years the cruel
<hi rend='italic'>Danes</hi> miserably ravaged this Kingdom, destroying,
by Fire and Sword, every Establishment,
as well of Piety as Learning, (to both which,
and to all religious Maxims of civilized Society,
they had been avowed implacable Enemies) till
they were themselves, in 1014, totally defeated
at <hi rend='italic'>Clontarf</hi>, by the invincible Arms of the Great
Monarch, <hi rend='italic'>Bryan Borou</hi>, from whom descended
a Race conspicuous for exemplary Prelates, heroick
Leaders, and steady Patriots.
</p>

<p>
The learned Author of the <hi rend='italic'>Dissertations</hi> before-mentioned,
charges this Hero with a Violation
of the Constitution of his Country: Yet the
Violation seems of far earlier Date, when the
supreme Monarchy was, by the <hi rend='italic'>Hugonian</hi> Law,
inalienably united to one Family, whose Sovereignty,
however founded originally, whether
by Birth, or Election, was essential to the public
<pb n='026'/><anchor id='Pg026'/>
Welfare: For we must allow that the Preservation
of the People is the principal Law to which all others are subordinate.
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Salus Populi
suprema Lex</foreign>; and equally, that not only the
Necessities, but the Safety also of the People, at
that Time of Danger and Distraction, eagerly
called forth the Conduct and Valour, the protective
and restorative Abilities of that great and
virtuous Man, of whom a faithful Historian,
in his Detail of the Battle of <hi rend='italic'>Clontarf</hi>, says;
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Integrâ prius adept a Victoriâ rebus
humanis eodem Diê excessit vir Bellô ac Pacê summus, Justitiæ,
Religionis, Literarum, Cultor eximius, et cum Carolo
Magno utique comparandus</foreign>.
</p>

<p>
In the 239th Page of the <hi rend='italic'>Dissertations</hi>, the excellent
Author expresseth himself as follows:
</p>

<p>
<q>I now proceed to give some Account of the
second Royal House of <hi rend='italic'>Scots</hi>, the oldest of the
<hi rend='italic'>Milesian</hi> Race, and the Posterity of
<hi rend='italic'>Eber</hi>.</q> This
Race then being avowed the oldest, in Respect
of Primogeniture, must, of Course, have been
prior in Point of Dignity and Sway, or at least,
equally entitled to the Election of the People
to such Ranks; were not those by violent Measures
annexed to the <hi rend='italic'>Heremonian</hi> Line: Yet, however
this might have been, certain it is, that no
Houses that we read of, ancient or modern,
have produced a greater Number of truly heroick
Princes, or of longer Continuance, than
those of the North and South <hi rend='italic'>Hy-Nial</hi>; from
whom also issued many noble Families of real
Worth, and equal Renown. With <hi rend='italic'>Bryan</hi>, the
happy Genius of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, in a great Measure,
expired: For the cruel <hi rend='italic'>Danes</hi> had, for near 200
Years before, so wofully overturned the Universities
of <hi rend='italic'>Ardmagh</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Dondaleith-Glass</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Mongret</hi>, and <hi rend='italic'>Lismore</hi>, with all
other Seminaries of Piety
<pb n='027'/><anchor id='Pg027'/>
and Learning, (the only genuine Sources of national
Greatness, Concord, good Discipline, and
Happiness) had obliged, in the 8th Century,
so many learned Men to seek that Shelter and
Security on the Continent, which the barbarous
Hostilities, and impious Manners of those Northerns,
denied them at Home; had made such
frequent lamentable Breaches in the antient, wise
Constitution of the Kingdom; had, by the fatal
Example of their profligate dissolute Lives, so
vitiated the national Morality; and finally, had
left behind them so many noxious Seeds of Faction
and Anarchy, as, in less than two Centuries,
gave up a Kingdom, of above 2000 Years
Establishment, the unaccountable Prey of a
few adventurous <hi rend='italic'>Normans</hi>!
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Patrick</hi> governed the See of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi> about
ten Years, and, in a Voyage to <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, perished
by Shipwreck, in the <hi rend='italic'>British</hi> Sea, on the
16th of <hi rend='italic'>October</hi>, 1084; having been sent to
<hi rend='italic'>Lanfranc</hi>, Archbishop of <hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>,
by King <hi rend='italic'>Tirdelvac</hi>.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Donat</hi>, or <hi rend='italic'>Dongus O'Haingly</hi>, having spent
some Time in the Study of useful Learning in
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, went over into <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>,
and became a Benedictine Monk at <hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>. He was afterwards,
(by the Consent of King <hi rend='italic'>Tirdelvac</hi>, and
the Clergy of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>) consecrated,
<hi rend='italic'>A. D.</hi> 1085, in the Cathedral of
<hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>, by the before-mentioned
<hi rend='italic'>Lanfranc</hi>, to whom he made the following
Profession of Obedience:
</p>

<p>
<q>I, <hi rend='italic'>Donat</hi>, Bishop of the See of
<hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi> in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, do promise
Canonical Obedience to you, <hi rend='italic'>O' Lanfranc</hi>, Archbishop of the
holy Church of <hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>, and to your Successors.</q>
</p>

<p>
It is evident that the Title of the Kings of
<hi rend='italic'>England</hi> to this Kingdom, by Papal Donation,
<pb n='028'/><anchor id='Pg028'/>
or Appointment, was very insufficient, if not
absolutely trifling: Nor could a Right of Conquest
be urged in any Period of the Reign of
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Second, or his Descendants. But
the Great and Royal Families of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, long
the Prey of Faction, deliberately preferred a
limitted and stipulated Submission to foreign
Authority, to the various Evils arising from
intestine Feuds and Animosities; and this, had
the wise Conditions thereof been constantly attended
to, with mutual Observance, had been
a sound Title, well and judiciously founded.
</p>

<p>
True it is, that after the Surrender of the
Crown by King <hi rend='italic'>John</hi> to the See of <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi>,
the Pope exerted some temporal Authority in this
Kingdom, instanced in his having created <hi rend='italic'>Mc.
Con More Mc. Namaras</hi><note place='foot'>This <hi rend='italic'>Mac Con More
Macnamara</hi>, Duke of <hi rend='italic'>Klan Cullane</hi>,
founded, erected, and amply endowed the beautiful Abbey
of <hi rend='italic'>Quin</hi>; as did other Chieftains of his Name and Family,
several Parochial Churches, with a great Number of magnificent
Castles.</note> Duke of <hi rend='italic'>Klan Cullane</hi>,
a Man of great Valour and Piety, supported by
ample Possessions in the Baronies of <hi rend='italic'>Tulla</hi> and
<hi rend='italic'>Bunratty</hi>, in the County of <hi rend='italic'>Clare</hi>;
which extensive Districts entirely belonged to that ancient,
hospitable, martial, and religious Race,
of which <hi rend='italic'>Mc. Con More</hi> was Chief: The <hi rend='italic'>Mc.
Namaras</hi>, more or less, have in all Ages made,
and still continue to make, a distinguished Figure,
as well in the Field, as in the learned Professions;
and were formerly so warlike a People,
that of themselves they formed an heroic Cavalry,
justly stiled the <hi rend='italic'>Phalanx</hi> of that Part of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> wherein they resided.
</p>

<p>
How our Neighbours came to call us <hi rend='italic'>waild
Ayrish</hi>, I am a Loss to conjecture; it being evident
<pb n='029'/><anchor id='Pg029'/>
we have been a thousand Years, at least,
in Possession of Letters, Laws, and Civility,
before the Arrival of <hi rend='italic'>Julius Cæsar</hi>
in <hi rend='italic'>Britain</hi>.
</p>

<p>
I am equally at a Loss to know why a Man
should become a standing Jest for his Ignorance
in an alien Tongue, almost the constant Fate of
our Countrymen in <hi rend='italic'>Britain</hi>, where, whoever is
not smartly expert in the <hi rend='italic'>English</hi> Language, is
immediately denominated a <hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi>, a
<hi rend='italic'>Paddy</hi>, or I know not what, in the Stile of Derision: At
the same Time that the most awkward-tongued
<hi rend='italic'>Irishman</hi> in <hi rend='italic'>London</hi> speaks
<hi rend='italic'>English</hi> with far more
Propriety, and a better Accent, than the smartest
<hi rend='italic'>British Petit Maitre</hi> in <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi> doth
<hi rend='italic'>French</hi>.
</p>

<p>
Some dramatick Scriblers, (probably of our
own degenerate Growth) the better to qualify
them for eleemosinary Dinners, gave Rise to this
impertinent Treatment of a Nation, which, from
the concurrent Testimonies of all the Dispassionate
and Learned, can, in Reality, be as little the
Object of Scurrility, as any other.
</p>

<p>
Why should even poor <hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi> prove so constant
a Butt, to Farce-wrights, and Hackney
Laughers; when, upon Examination, he is, by
a thousand Degrees, preferable to the <hi rend='italic'>British</hi>
Hobbinol, or <hi rend='italic'>French</hi> Gregoire? For
<hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi> is
a very Pattern of Hospitality; so much so, that
if a Gentleman should happen to miss his Road,
and be nessitated to seek the Shelter of <hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi>'s
Cabbin, or Hut, was poor <hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi> trusting to
two Sheep for his worldly Subsistance, he would
kill one, and sell the other, at the next Village
or Inn, for the better Entertainment of his
Guest, and think himself happy in such an
Occasion of approving his Generosity and Respect:
He would the next Morning abandon his
Spade, and chearfully trot ten Miles to shew
<pb n='030'/><anchor id='Pg030'/>
such bewilder'd Gentleman the right Road. He
is naturally civil, generous, and hospitable, (for
scarce a Night passeth that poor Travellers are
not entertained in his Cottage,) extremely respectful
to his Superiors, and to his Lord and
Master faithful to Death. The military Annals
of <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi> proclaim his Capacity and Taste for
Fighting; then if you should take this identical
<hi rend='italic'>Teague</hi>'s infant Son, and give him a regular
liberal Education, it is one hundred to one,
but he turns out a Gentleman of Merit, Learning,
Worth, and Politeness; whereas it would
certainly require more than <hi rend='italic'>Herculean</hi>
Labour to chissel a <hi rend='italic'>French Paisan</hi>, a primitive
<hi rend='italic'>Westmoreland</hi>, or <hi rend='italic'>Devonshire</hi> Boor,
not only into the Form of an elegant, but even into that
of a sociable Creature.
</p>

<p>
The Insignificancy of those Jesters and Spatterers,
will more clearly appear, if we look
back to the wise, free, and truly parliamentary
Constitution of this Kingdom; if we recollect
the vast Length of its Duration, as a free and
independant State; the military Prowess of its
Inhabitants in all Ages; their victorious Conflicts
with the <hi rend='italic'>Romans</hi>, and with the <hi rend='italic'>French</hi>
under <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Vth, and the Black
<hi rend='italic'>Prince</hi>; their having founded a Monarchy in
<hi rend='italic'>North Britain</hi>, whence, by a Right of Descent, in Addition to
every other, his present Majesty, (whom God
long preserve,) by the special Providence and
infinite Mercy of Heaven, ruleth over us: If
we consider the Number of our Universities,
Colleges, and Academies, religious Monasteries
and pious Seminaries, resorted to from all
civilized Parts of <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>, our Metropolitical
and Diocesan Cathedrals; on such impartial Review,
surely, the foregoing Tribe of Sneerers
<pb n='031'/><anchor id='Pg031'/>
and Flouters must dwindle into deserved Contempt.
</p>

<p>
I shall close this feeble Attempt on the antient
State of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, with the Description thereof
by <hi rend='italic'>Donat</hi>, Bishop of <hi rend='italic'>Fesulæ</hi>, near
<hi rend='italic'>Florence</hi>, in the 7th or 8th Century; referring, at the same
Time, to the most authentick <hi rend='italic'>British</hi> Antiquaries,
<hi rend='italic'>Campden</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Giraldus Cambrensis</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Buchanan</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Ware</hi>, &amp;c. for
Confirmation of what hath been previously observed on the same Subject.
</p>

<lg>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Finibus Occiduis describitur
optima Tellus,</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Nomine et Antiquis
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Scotia</hi> scripta Libris&mdash;&mdash;</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Insula dives Opum, Gemmarum,
Vestis et Auri,</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Commoda Corporibus, Aere sole
Solo;</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Melle fluit pulchris et
lacteis <hi rend='smallcaps'>Scotia</hi> Campis</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Vestibus atque Armis,
frugibus, arte viris.</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Ursorum Rabies, nulla est ibi;
sæva Leonum</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Semina, nec unquam
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Scotica</hi> Terra tulit</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Nulla Venena nocent, nec
Serpens serpit in Herbâ,</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Nec conquesta canit
Garula Rana Lacu;</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">In qua
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Scotorum</hi> Gentes habitare merentur</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend="font-style: italic">Inclita Gens Hominum
Milite, Pace, Fide.</foreign></l>
</lg>

<p>
Thus Englished by the Ingenius and Reverend
Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Dunkin</hi>:
</p>

<lg>
<l><q rend="pre">Far Westward, lies an Isle of antient Fame,</q></l>
<l>By Nature bless'd, and <hi rend='smallcaps'>Scotia</hi> is her Name;</l>
<l>Enroll'd in Books: Exhaustless is her Store</l>
<l>Of veiny Silver, and of Golden Ore:</l>
<l>Her fruitful Soil for ever teams with Wealth,</l>
<l>With Gems her Waters, and her Air with Health:</l>
<l>Her verdant Fields with Milk and Honey flow;</l>
<l>Her woolly Fleeces vie with Virgin Snow:</l>
<pb n='032'/><anchor id='Pg032'/>
<l>Her waving Furrows float with bearded Corn,</l>
<l>And Arms and Arts her envy'd Sons adorn.</l>
<l>No savage Bear, with lawless Fury, roves;</l>
<l>No rav'nous Lion, thro' her peaceful Groves;</l>
<l>No Poison there infects; no scaly Snake</l>
<l>Creeps thro' the Grass, nor Frog annoys the Lake:</l>
<l>An Island worthy of its pious Race,</l>
<l><q rend="post">In War triumphant, and unmatch'd in Peace.</q></l>
</lg>

<p>
This <hi rend='italic'>Donat</hi>, Bishop of <hi rend='italic'>Fesula</hi>, was an
<hi rend='italic'>Irishman</hi>, of the antient and hospitable Family, afterwards
<hi rend='italic'>O Hogan</hi>; a Family which held ample and
fair Possessions in the Province of <hi rend='italic'>Munster</hi>, and
which, in former Times, adorned the See of
<hi rend='italic'>Killaloe</hi>, with four very learned and exemplary
Prelates; namely, with <hi rend='italic'>Matthew O Hogan</hi>, who
succeeded to this Bishoprick, in the Reign of
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the IIId, and in the Year of our Lord
1267; and who, having much enlarged his Diocese,
and done many signal Acts of popular Charity,
died in the Year, 1281, and was buried
in <hi rend='italic'>Limerick</hi>, in a Convent of <hi rend='italic'>Dominican</hi>
Friars. To this Bishop succeeded <hi rend='italic'>Maurice O Hogan</hi>,
who governed this See with peculiar Zeal and
Charity, upwards of sixteen Years, and died in
1298, or the Year following, and was buried
in his own Church. <hi rend='italic'>Thomas O Hogan</hi>, Canon
of <hi rend='italic'>Killaloe</hi>, was consecrated in 1343, and died
on the 30th of <hi rend='italic'>October</hi>, 1354; five Days after
which, he was buried among his worthy Ancestors
at <hi rend='italic'>Nenagh</hi>; as may be seen in the Annals
of that Place.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Richard O Hogan</hi> succeeded to the See of
<hi rend='italic'>Killaloe</hi>, in 1525, and was in 1539 translated to
<hi rend='italic'>Clon Mac Nois</hi>: He was a Prelate of great
<pb n='033'/><anchor id='Pg033'/>
Learning and Capacity, in all spiritual and ecclesiastical
Matters.
</p>

<p>
This antient Family is, at this Time, represented
by <hi rend='italic'>Edmund O Hogan</hi>, Esq; High Sheriff
of the County of <hi rend='italic'>Clare</hi>, a Gentleman, who,
by the whole Tenor of his Life, hath proved
Generosity of Heart, Charity, and Hospitality,
to be Qualities inherent.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Dermod Mac Murchad</hi>, sovereign Prince of
<hi rend='italic'>Hy-Kinsellagh</hi>, banished by <hi rend='italic'>Roderick O
Connor</hi>, King of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, for his various and high State
Crimes, sought Sanctuary and Redress in the
Court of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>; where, in the Absence of
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi>, then in <hi rend='italic'>Normandy</hi>, diverse
adventurous <hi rend='italic'>Normans</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Flemings</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Saxons</hi>, and old <hi rend='italic'>Britons</hi>, (being
themselves unsettled, and unestablished) acceded
to the Fate and Fortunes of <hi rend='italic'>Dermod</hi>, under
the Conduct of <hi rend='italic'>Strongbow</hi>, Earl of
<hi rend='italic'>Pembroke</hi>; whose casual Success in
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, against <hi rend='italic'>Roderick</hi>
(owing <emph>more</emph> to the general Defection, at that
fatal Period, of the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Chiefs against their
lawful Sovereign, than to any <emph>superior Valour</emph> or
Address of those Adventurers) induced <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> to
a deliberate and grand Invasion of a Kingdom,
to which he could lay no Claim on the Score of
Nature, Reason, or Right, and whither his
pretended Mission, on the Score of collecting
St. <hi rend='italic'>Peter</hi>'s Dues, (which St. <hi rend='italic'>Peter</hi>
himself never once thought of, or imagined) was as <emph>ridiculous</emph>
as <emph>groundless</emph>. The <hi rend='italic'>Summa Dies</hi>, however, arrived:
and the People of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, wearied out
with intestine Strife, acknowledged <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> for
their Sovereign Lord; and a grand Charter of
Rights and Covenants, mutual Protection and
Allegiance, was entered into, anteriorly to that
of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>. How well this Charter was <emph>observed</emph>
on the <emph>protective</emph> Side, the absolute Anarchy of
<pb n='034'/><anchor id='Pg034'/>
near four Centuries, from its original Date and
Perfection, to the Reign of Queen <hi rend='italic'>Elizabeth</hi>,
demonstrates: A whole Nation, that sought
Protection, and that <emph>agreed</emph> for quiet, regular,
and lawful Government, upon rationable Terms,
deprived of the Power of ordaining Laws for
its own Security and Well-being, and precluded
(all to four or five great and favourite Families)
from the Benefits and Advantages accruing from
those of that Kingdom, to which it had voluntarily
united itself; exposed, through such a
Length of Time, to arbitary Depredations, and
unpunished, unredressed, uncensured Rapine,
<hi rend='italic'>Quis talia sando temperet a Lachrymis</hi>!
</p>

<p>
King <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> called back into <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>,
to lay the Storms raised by his rebellious Sons, with
whom and <hi rend='italic'>Thomas Becket</hi>, Archbishop of
<hi rend='italic'>Canterbury</hi>,
he was so constantly embroiled to the
End of his Life, that he could little attend to
the Settlement of the Affairs of this new acquired
Sovereignty.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Richard</hi> the First, his immediate Successor,
called away to the Holy Wars against the <hi rend='italic'>Saracens</hi>,
had as little Leisure as his Predecessor to
promote the Quiet, or Happiness of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<p>
From the usurped Authority of King <hi rend='italic'>John</hi>, a
continued Series of Papal Animosity, Bloodshed,
Calamities and Piracies, closed at last by
Poison; little beside political Disasters of all
Sorts, could be expected.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Third, through a Reign of Fifty-six
Years, was continually involved in Troubles
and Hostilities, with his inflexible <hi rend='italic'>English</hi> Barons.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Edward</hi> the First, a great and warlike Prince,
was, throughout his whole Reign, engaged in
the Reduction of the <hi rend='italic'>Welch</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Scots</hi>,
and so
<pb n='035'/><anchor id='Pg035'/>
intent thereon, that he could turn his Thoughts
to no other Object.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Edward</hi> the Second, indeed, sent
<hi rend='italic'>Gaveston</hi> hither,
more to screen him from the implacable
Resentments of the stubborn <hi rend='italic'>English</hi> Nobility,
than to render any good Offices to the Inhabitants
of this Country; who, indiscriminately,
(<hi rend='italic'>Strongbownians</hi> as well as <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>)
felt the Severity of that insolent Favourite's Measures.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Richard</hi> the Second visited this Kingdom in
Person, with the good Intentions of establishing
Peace, Order, and Harmony, in a valuable but
long neglected Estate: Yet his own adverse
Fate, conspiring with that of this Land, called
him back, before he could carry his favourable
Resolutions into Execution, to defend his <hi rend='italic'>English</hi>
Dominions from the hostile Attacks of <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi>,
Earl of <hi rend='italic'>Hereford</hi>, who, with the Duke of
<hi rend='italic'>Norfolk</hi>, Son to <hi rend='italic'>John</hi> of
<hi rend='italic'>Gaunt</hi>, had some Years before
been banished by <hi rend='italic'>Richard</hi>, to prevent a
personal Combat: This King, worthy more
propitious Stars, long agitated and afflicted by
the Turbulence and irreconcilable Obstinacy of
his <hi rend='italic'>British</hi> Subjects, perished at last under the
impious Hands of Sir <hi rend='italic'>Pierce</hi> of <hi rend='italic'>Exton</hi>,
who, at the Head of eight barbarous armed Assassins,
rushed into his Chamber, and murdered him.
</p>

<p>
The Reign of <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Fourth was short,
tumultuous, and bloody; Deluges of noble Blood
having been shed by the bare Hands of the
common Executioner, to confirm a Throne acquired
by abominable Crimes, and Violence!
And no sooner had these dreadful Storms begun
to abate, than <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> was forced to depart from
a Scene he had more adorned, (for he was,
without Question, a great and valiant Man)
<pb n='036'/><anchor id='Pg036'/>
had not his Ambition blindly hurried him beyond
the Bounds of Justice and Nature.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Fifth, his Son and Successor, and
truly Inheritor of his Ambition and warlike
Genius, imagining himself aggrieved by the
<hi rend='italic'>Salique Law</hi>, which excluded his Great Great-Grandmother,
<hi rend='italic'>Isabel</hi>, from the Monarchy of
<hi rend='italic'>France</hi>, turned his elevated Thoughts intirely
to the Conquest of that Kingdom: Wherein,
by his own vast Merit in martial Affairs, and
the Co-operation of the Queen of <hi rend='italic'>France</hi>, (Consort
of <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the Sixth, then frantick,) and that
of the Duke of <hi rend='italic'>Burgundy</hi>, a great and powerful
Prince, he so far succeeded, as, after his Marriage
with <hi rend='italic'>Catharine de Valois</hi>, Daughter of
<hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the Sixth, to be crowned, and acknowledged
King of <hi rend='italic'>France</hi>.
</p>

<p>
To this great and victorious Monarch succeeded
<hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Sixth, who, through a long,
various, and constantly clouded Reign, seemed
the very Play of Fortune! This Day a King,
the next a Prisoner! One Day acknowleged by
his Parliament, the next attainted! One Day a
Conqueror, and the next a Captive!
</p>

<p>
Fierce, frequent, and bloody, were the Conflicts
between the Houses of <hi rend='italic'>York</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Lancaster</hi>,
the <hi rend='italic'>White</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Red Roses</hi>; the former
endeavouring to recover its Loss, the latter to maintain
its usurped Authority. In this dreadful Quarrel
perished two hundred thousand of private Soldiers;
ten thousand of the Nobility, Gentry,
and Persons of Distinction; three Kings; and,
at last, the entire Race of <hi rend='italic'>Plantagenet</hi>.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Edward</hi> the Fourth soon fell, by his natural
Intemperance, or rather by the insatiable Cruelty
of <hi rend='italic'>Gloucester</hi>; who had already sacrificed his
Brother <hi rend='italic'>Clarence</hi>, to pave his Way to the Throne.
<pb n='037'/><anchor id='Pg037'/>
Nor better fared it with <hi rend='italic'>Edward</hi> the Fifth, who,
by all the Arts of Seduction and Delusion,
which his unnatural Uncle and Guardian,
<hi rend='italic'>Richard</hi>, practised on the Fears and Weakness
of the Queen Dowager; was, with his Brother
the Duke of <hi rend='italic'>York</hi>, conveyed with great Pomp
to the Tower; where the bloody Tyrant, aided
by the Duke of <hi rend='italic'>Buckingham</hi>, soon sacrificed
those young, innocent and hopeful Princes to
his wicked and boundless Ambition. But he
soon after lost his own flagitious Life, and a
most cruelly-acquired Crown, on the Plains of
<hi rend='italic'>Bosworth</hi>.
</p>

<p>
To him succeeded <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Seventh, and the
first of the Race of <hi rend='italic'>Tudor</hi>, a great, wise and
valiant Prince, but rather too much inclined to
Rigour, and Avarice; Imperfections which extremely
blemished his other great Qualities.
</p>

<p>
In the tenth Year of this Reign, the Parliamentary
Constitution of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> received a
deeper Stab than had ever before, or since, been
inflicted thereon, by a Statute Law, commonly
called <hi rend='italic'>Poynin</hi>'s Act; by which a new, and, till
that wretched Period, an unheard of Order, was
added to the three established Ranks of the
State. By this Law, the <hi rend='italic'>English</hi> Privy-Council
may impose a <hi rend='italic'>Negative</hi> on the <emph>free</emph> and
<emph>unanimous</emph> Parliamentary Ordinances of the representative
Body of the Kingdom of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>; a manifest
Injury to the Authority and Dignity of Parliament;
and an equal Diminution of the Royal
Prerogative, that only should include, and
should alone exert, a Power so important.
</p>

<p>
In Times dark, tumultuated and dangerous,
no Wonder extraordinary Laws should pass:
<hi rend='italic'>Desperate Diseases</hi> require <hi rend='italic'>desperate
Remedies</hi>: But when the <hi rend='italic'>Fever</hi> is removed, it certainly is a
<pb n='038'/><anchor id='Pg038'/>
horrid Management to leave the blistering
Plaister <emph>still sticking</emph> to the <emph>recovered</emph> Patient's
Back.
</p>

<p>
The Distempers of this Nation were heavy,
complicated and chronic; and finally curable,
only by the salutary all-healing Hands of our
present King, and present Parliament.
</p>

<p>
To <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the Seventh succeeded <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the
Eighth, as consummate a Tyrant, in every
Sense, as ever swayed the <hi rend='italic'>British</hi>, or any other
Sceptre; whose whole Life was so continued a
Scene of wanton Dissipation, Lust, Cruelty,
Rapine, Bloodshed and Sacrilege, that it must
have been a peculiar Happiness, to any Part of
his Dominions, to have been <emph>neglected</emph> or <emph>forgotten</emph>
by him: Nor could the two succeeding
Reigns of <hi rend='italic'>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen
<hi rend='italic'>Mary</hi>,
short, various, cloudy, and vastly agitated on
the Score of Religion, (which, in those two
Reigns, took Faces almost diametrically opposite,)
afford this Kingdom much reflected
Sunshine.
</p>

<p>
To those ensued that of Queen <hi rend='italic'>Elizabeth</hi>, a
Princess of powerful Abilities, who, truly intent
on the Peace and Welfare of her Subjects,
caused her Laws to operate, and Justice to circulate
in this Kingdom, abandoned, as hath
been observed, to a State almost of Anarchy,
thro' a dismal Series of seventeen Reigns: But
the Reformation in Religion, which she established
in <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, and introduced in <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>,
much obviated her Purposes for the latter Kingdom:
For, the <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, more tenacious of their
Altars, than of their Fire-places, could not
easily reconcile themselves to the Exchange of a
Religion they deemed a <emph>new one</emph>, for <emph>that</emph> they
had been in Possession of from the fourth, to
<pb n='039'/><anchor id='Pg039'/>
the fifteenth Century: Which produced a rebellious
Defection, in a few of the principal
Chieftains of this Land, and gave Occasion to
the greedy Provincial Precedents, of trumping
up <emph>imaginary Rebellions</emph>, to pave the Way to <emph>real
Forfeitures</emph>; thereby to aggrandize their own
Houses; what some of them effectually accomplished,
to the Ruin and Extirpation of
many honest Families.
</p>

<p>
This great and illustrious Princess, (whose
Reign had remained untarnished, had it not
been for the Death of the ill-fated Queen of
<hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>) was succeeded by <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the
Sixth of <hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>, and the first of the
<hi rend='italic'>Stuart</hi> Race that governed <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>: From
this Prince, descended of <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Kings, the People of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> might have expected many Favours and Immunities;
wherein, however, they were miserably disappointed:
Which, with a Train of other Hardships
and antiparental Severities, (particularly
his alienating, at <emph>one Stroke</emph>, six of the best
Counties in the Kingdom, on the <emph>procured</emph> Testimony
of an obscure wretched Individual, one
<hi rend='italic'>Teige Lenane</hi>,) is too sufficient and too lasting a
Proof of: <hi rend='italic'>Heu! tot Conquesta Annorum, hauserit
una Dies!</hi> The Possession of at least twenty
Centuries, of the great and good, the heroic
and hospitable <hi rend='italic'>O Neils</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Donnels</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Mac Guires</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Gennises</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Reillys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Cahanes</hi>, &amp;c. ravished
away to gratify hungry Favourites, and indigent
Relatives! the six Counties, however, as the
Law Term has it, <hi rend='italic'>escheated</hi>. Had the
<hi rend='italic'>Highlands</hi> of <hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>, at that unhappy
Period, been more populated, probably six or eight Counties <emph>more</emph>
had been procured to <hi rend='italic'>escheat</hi>, and there had been
<hi rend='italic'>a braa Clutch of bonny Traitors</hi>; the
<hi rend='italic'>O Connors</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Carthys</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Briens</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Donnels</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Hares</hi>,
<pb n='040'/><anchor id='Pg040'/>
<hi rend='italic'>O Malones</hi>, &amp;c. had been <emph>all</emph> in the
<emph>same Bottom</emph> with the Families above mentioned; especially,
as they could not, according to <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the First's
own Phrase, <hi rend='italic'>look to the Pope, and row with
him</hi>.
</p>

<p>
To <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the 6th of <hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>, and first
of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, succeeded <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the First;
who, notwithstanding his eminent Possession of all the
Virtues that adorn and illustrate human Nature,
could neither divert the adverse Fate of Subjects,
or prevent his own.
</p>

<p>
The Disseisin of many honest Families in the
County of <hi rend='italic'>Kilkenny</hi>, and elsewhere, by the Earl
of <hi rend='italic'>Strafford</hi>, on stale Pretences of <hi rend='italic'>Non
Performance of Covenants</hi> on their Part; his Attempt of
confiscating twenty-five Parts in thirty of the
whole Province of <hi rend='italic'>Connaught</hi>, on a Claim of
Descent, dormant 300 Years, and <emph>originally ill
founded</emph>, with the arbitrary Steps by him taken to
the Accomplishment of this wasteful Purpose;
too clearly proved that Nobleman a second
<hi rend='italic'>Verres</hi>. The cruel and intoxicated Administration
of the Rump Parliament; the insolent, licentious,
and riotous Controul of the military
<hi rend='italic'>Independents</hi>; the abject Tyranny of <hi rend='italic'>Oliver
Cromwell</hi>, who prostrated Constitution, Church
and State, will always be recollected with the
Contempt, Horror, and Detestation of every
good Subject.
</p>

<p>
The Calamities from 1641, to the happy Restoration
of King <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the Second, in 1660,
being common to all good Subjects, were the
more tolerable, <foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>ferre quam sortem
patiuntur omnes, nemo recusat</foreign>: But now or never, surely, might
his ever loyal, ever faithful <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Subjects have,
with the most reasonable Assurance, hoped, if
not for publick and lasting Rewards, the common
<pb n='041'/><anchor id='Pg041'/>
Wages of uncommon Fidelity; at least,
for a Restitution of what had been their own,
through Ages immemorial.
</p>

<p>
Will late Posterity <emph>believe</emph>, that, in Favour of
mercenary Adventurers, who advanced Money
to provide for a desperate regicide Army; in
Favour of the Officers of this same Army, whom
their Ringleader <hi rend='italic'>Cromwell</hi>, seared as his Conscience
was, indulged with no more than <emph>temporary</emph>
Grants of the Estates belonging to the
King's most faithful Subjects: Will Posterity,
I say, believe, that, in special Favour of such
Men, those <emph>identical Subjects</emph>, the bravest Advocates,
as well as the most affectionate undeviating
Friends of the Monarchy and Constitution,
were <emph>for ever</emph> deprived of their Properties! To
remunerate the <emph>others</emph>, the most <emph>inveterate</emph> and
<emph>implacable</emph> Enemies of <hi rend='smallcaps'>EITHER</hi>! <emph>Doing
Good for Evil</emph> is a Divine Precept, and certainly includes
a most sublime Moral; but <emph>rendering Evil for
Good</emph>, is such a Principle as must carry Horror
with it, among savage Nations!
</p>

<p>
The King of <hi rend='italic'>France</hi>'s immediate Letter, on
this Subject, to King <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the Second, as it
reflects Honour on the Memory of those illustrious
Sufferers, I therefore take Leave to transcribe
in this Place.
</p>

<milestone unit="tb" rend="stars: 5"/>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>His Most Christian Majesty's Letter to the King of
<hi rend='italic'>Great Britain</hi>, in Favour of the <hi rend='italic'>Roman
Catholicks</hi> of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.</hi>
</p>

<quote rend="display">
<q>Most High, Most Excellent, and Most
Potent Prince, our dear and well-beloved Brother
and Cousin! At the same Time that we
have been told of your Majesty's great Goodness
towards your Subjects, and the Precedent
<pb n='042'/><anchor id='Pg042'/>
you have given of an extraordinary Clemency,
in granting them your general Amnesty
(some few only excepted, of those
whom the Blood of their King, and that of
his People, cry aloud to Heaven for Revenge
against). We could not but let your Majesty
know, that we were extremely surprized to
hear, that the <hi rend='italic'>Catholicks</hi> of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>
were <emph>excluded</emph> from that Act of Oblivion, and, by
that Means, put into the Number of the <emph>most
criminal</emph>! This News has so much the more
excited our Compassion towards them, that
we have been informed, that, in <emph>all the
Changes</emph> which have hitherto happened in your
Dominions, and in the almost general <emph>Defection
of</emph> your Subjects, <emph>none</emph> stood <emph>more constant</emph>
to their lawful Sovereign, even in the greatest
Streights, than the <hi rend='italic'>Catholicks</hi>: So that, if
they are now branded for their Religion, it
may be said, for their Honour, that, in
Times past, none could be found <emph>readier</emph>, or
more <emph>cheerfully disposed</emph>, than <emph>they</emph>, to serve
and assist their Prince; and that with so
much <emph>Ardour</emph>, that their Zeal then for the
Royal Family was reckoned a certain Mark
of their true Religion. It is for that Reason
that we now become their Intercessors to you:
For, otherwise, had they <emph>failed</emph> in the Fidelity
they owe you, instead of interceding for
them, we would join with you in using them
with all imaginable Rigour; and it would
never come into our Thoughts to concern
ourselves, as we do, for the <hi rend='italic'>Catholicks</hi> of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>; though we <emph>were obliged to it</emph>, by the last
Treaty of Peace made with the Marquess of
<hi rend='italic'>Ormond</hi>, and which was granted them by our
Mediation. And, as we are well assured,
<pb n='043'/><anchor id='Pg043'/>
that, since the Conclusion of that Peace, they
have done Nothing which can be called a
<emph>Failure of their Duty to you</emph>, we find ourselves
under so much the greater Obligation to conjure
you, to make good that Treaty to them,
in that they <emph>religiously</emph> observed it on <emph>their</emph>
Side, in all its Parts: And to beseech you
not to suffer, that either the Hatred, which
an immoderate Zeal swells some bigotted Sectaries
with, nor the unlucky Spoils of these
poor People, render criminal or miserable the
<emph>most faithful</emph> of your Subjects; to whom their
lawful King, as you are, is not <emph>the less dear</emph>,
nor <emph>less respected</emph>, because of a <emph>different Belief</emph>
from <emph>theirs</emph>. We propose Nothing to ourselves
in this, nor ask any Thing, but what
we daily <emph>practise</emph> (as you may know) towards
those of our Subjects who are of the <emph>reformed
Religion</emph>. And, as we have commanded the
Sieur Marquis <hi rend='italic'>de Rouvigny</hi> to explain our
Sentiments more amply on this Subject to
you, be pleased to give him a favourable Audience:
And, above all Things, be perswaded,
that, in this Affair, we have no less your
own <emph>true Interest</emph> in View, than what <emph>natural
Reason</emph> and <emph>Equity</emph> requires; and that our sincere
Friendship for you is the principal Motive
of this Request. Dated at <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, the 7th
of <hi rend='italic'>September</hi>, 1660.</q>
</quote>

<p>
The <emph>good</emph> King <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi>, regardless of this important
Solicitation, unattentive to the plain Suggestions
of <emph>common Right</emph>, and unaccountably
forgetful of all their <emph>past signal Services</emph> and inviolate
Zeal; observed indeed that those faithful
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Subjects had no Stock; consequently, that
dispossessing the Adherents of <hi rend='italic'>Oliver</hi>, who, with
<pb n='044'/><anchor id='Pg044'/>
the Land, had pirated the national Stock, would
cause much Confusion. As for the <emph>former</emph>, he
hoped some Settlement might in Time be found
for them; (in Truth, I believe, for aught his
Majesty in Reality concerned himself, this might
have been in <hi rend='italic'>Terra Australis Incognita</hi>). Their
Want of Stock is the less to be admired at, it
being well known, that, with their Pay in foreign
Service, chiefly expended to contribute all
in their Power to the <hi rend='italic'>Royal Support</hi>, they even
went so far as to sell their Plate, and valuable
Moveables, to answer the same <emph>generous Purpose</emph>:
But, when every known Acre in the Kingdom,
that could be disposed of, was given away
by Wholesale to the Duke of <hi rend='italic'>York</hi>, the Heir-apparent
of the Crown, (partial Distribution!)
to new-fangled Favourites, and the staunch old
Enemies of Church and Crown; it was hoped
some Lands might be <emph>yet</emph> discovered, to satisfy
and compensate those <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Worthies, who had
Nothing left for their Support, beside an inalienable
Sense of Honour and Loyalty, and a Character
of invincible Fidelity (which all Nations
admired and applauded). No such Discovery,
however, was made, nor any relative to the
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>, under that Administration, but what
tended to convince them, by the famous Act
of Settlement, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi> of the extraordinary severe
Peculiarity of their Fate! Yet, ordained to
shew Posterity unprecedented Specimens of Loyalty
and Zeal, they still adhered, with inflexible
Constancy, to the Fortunes of King <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the
Second, not mindful of their Injuries by <hi rend='italic'>James</hi>
the First, their unexampled Sufferings by the
excessive harsh Measures of King <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> the
First, his Ministers, and Deputies, or their unheard-of
Treatment (I won't say <emph>Wrongs</emph>, it
<pb n='045'/><anchor id='Pg045'/>
being a Maxim the King of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi> can do none)
by King <hi rend='italic'>Charles</hi> II. Little Wonder, a House,
constantly sapping it's own best Pillars, should
at length fall.
</p>

<p>
King <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the Second, constrained to abdicate
the Throne of <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, endeavoured the
Preservation of this his Kingdom of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>,
where his faithful Subjects, (a Remnant of the
various and manifold Wastes of foregoing
Reigns) considering the thousand Disadvantages
they laboured under, made <emph>such a Stand</emph> as later
Ages will look up to with Astonishment! A
Parcel of Men, congregated in the utmost Hurry
and Confusion, undisciplin'd, unarm'd, uncloathed,
unpaid! Yet did those very Men,
animated by the Example of their heroick Leaders,
(I mean their immediate Lords and Countrymen)
on the Plains of <hi rend='italic'>Aughrim</hi>, convince
the best veteran Army that Day in <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>, superior
in Numbers, excellently provided for in
every Respect, and conducted by a Prince of
singular Valour and Address, that <hi rend='italic'>Irishmen</hi> were
deserving of more auspicious Stars.
</p>

<p>
Never was a more gallant Defence than they,
after this, made in <hi rend='italic'>Limerick</hi>; where, although
abandoned by the Prince, (whose Cause they
had so remarkably espoused) and his auxiliary
<hi rend='italic'>French</hi>, they obtained an honourable
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Capitulation</hi> from those in Commission under King
<hi rend='italic'>William</hi> the Third, whose strict <emph>Observance</emph>
thereof, to the End of his glorious Life, reflects,
among many other his great Atchievements,
deserved Honour on his Memory.
</p>

<p>
The distinguished Figure made by those
Noblemen and Gentlemen, who, regardless of
<emph>Property</emph> or <emph>Ease</emph>, followed the Destiny of that
hard-fated Prince, King <hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the Second,
<pb n='046'/><anchor id='Pg046'/>
(namely, the Lords <hi rend='italic'>Mount-Cashel</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Tyrconnel</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Clare</hi> and <hi rend='italic'>Lucan</hi>, the
<hi rend='italic'>Dillons</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Nugents</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Rooths</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Burkes</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Lees</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Fitz-Geralds</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Cooks</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Lacys</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Browns</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Wogans</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Baggots</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Sheridans</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Creaghs</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Plunkets</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Barnewals</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Neagles</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Lallys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Carthys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac
Donnels</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Guires</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Namarras</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Mac Mahons</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mac Gennis's</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Neils</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Connors</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Donnels</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Briens</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Dwyers</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Shaghnussys</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Mahonys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Sullivans</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Kellys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Ferralls</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Reillys</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Haras</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Hogans</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>O Byrnes</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>O Daes</hi>, &amp;c.
&amp;c. &amp;c. the military Annals of <hi rend='italic'>Germany</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>France</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Flanders</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Italy</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Naples</hi>, and
<hi rend='italic'>Russia</hi>), must bear ample and authentic Testimony
of, to future Ages.
</p>

<p>
Those were they, of whom Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Mac en Crow</hi>
gives the following concise, but just and happy
Character.
</p>

<quote rend="display">
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Genus acre Bello, Studiis Genus acre
Minervæ, Devotumque mori pro Rege, Fidêque tuendis.</foreign>
</quote>

<p>
Among those who followed the Fortunes of King
<hi rend='italic'>James</hi> the Second, were Sir <hi rend='italic'>Richard Neagle</hi>,
his Attorney-General, and Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Moore</hi>, Provost
of <hi rend='italic'>Trinity-college</hi>, near <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>; two
Gentlemen very justly distinguished in their respective
Spheres; the former, a Gentleman of unshaken
Integrity, and great Capacity in the Profession
of the Laws; the latter, of exemplary Piety,
universal Learning, and fine Accomplishments.
<hi rend='italic'>Louis</hi> the Fourteenth, then King of <hi rend='italic'>France</hi>,
protected those worthy deserving Men, with singular
Tenderness and Attention; and was instructed
and guided solely by Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Moore</hi>, in the restoring,
establishing, and modelling the University
of <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, at that gloomy Period! quite
buried in perplexed, unintelligible, peripatetic
<pb n='047'/><anchor id='Pg047'/>
Philosophy, and disfigured with romantic Legends,
and Gothic Jingle! But, at the Doctor's
Appearance, Entities, Quiddities, Sympathies,
Antipathies, occult Qualities, substantial
Forms, metaphysical Degrees, Categories, and
all this unideal wordy Stuff, vanished; and
were succeeded by a clear, concise Method of
Reasoning, and sound, useful, and experimental
Philosophy. <hi rend='italic'>Greek</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Hebrew</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Syriac</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Chaldaic</hi>,
and <hi rend='italic'>Arabic</hi>, were Languages <emph>untaught</emph>,
<emph>unknown</emph>, in the University of <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, before Dr.
<hi rend='italic'>Moore</hi>; for whom particularly, <hi rend='italic'>Louis</hi> the
Fourteenth founded, established, and endowed the Royal
College, now called <hi rend='italic'>College du Cambray</hi>: And
how well our Doctor succeeded therein, may be
inferred from the Character and Writings of
his Pupils and Hearers, <hi rend='italic'>Boileau</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Fontinelle</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Poréc</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Montesquieu</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Fleuri</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Lauguet</hi>, with many
others, and <hi rend='italic'>Rollin</hi>, his peculiar Favourite and
immediate Successor, <hi rend='italic'>all</hi> great Genius's, applauded
Writers, and celebrated Wits. So
that, as <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> had the Honour of founding, it
had also that of restoring and reviving the great
University of <hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>, in the Persons of two of
its learned Natives.
</p>

<p>
The Reign of her Majesty Queen <hi rend='italic'>Anne</hi> (glorious
to her Arms, under the Conduct of <hi rend='italic'>John</hi>,
Duke of <hi rend='italic'>Marlborough</hi>, and her other Generals,
and justly distinguished by the Number of great
Genius's and Wits, who enlightened that Period)
was in this Kingdom chiefly employed in
<emph>additional</emph> Acts against the further Growth of
Popery: And many there were, who deemed it
an unparallel'd Severity in her Majesty, to give
her Royal Assent to them particular Laws; by
which the <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholicks</hi> of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>
(already ruined by their inimitable Allegiance to her
<pb n='048'/><anchor id='Pg048'/>
Royal Father, Uncle, and Grandfather) were
<emph>precluded</emph> from availing themselves, by a tolerable
easy Lease, of any Part or Parcel of these Estates,
forfeited by their Ancestors, thro' their
unremitting Endeavours, to support and maintain
that Stem, of which she was herself an immediate
Branch.
</p>

<p>
So late even as this Reign, the whole Kingdom
of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> was a desolate diffusive Scene of
total Decay! covered with all the ghastly Symptoms
of the Consumption of Centuries! But,
at length, on the happy Accession of his late
Majesty of glorious Memory, the blissful Morning
of Peace and Concord began its auspicious
Dawn! Yet, as Time, publick Spirit, Patriotism
(in its highest Conception) and unwearied
Diligence, were all collectively essential to the
giving Life, Vigour, and Activity, to national
Industry and Improvement, so very long in a
melancholy State of Languor and Oppression:
Not before the present truly glorious Reign, did
<hi rend='italic'>Hibernia</hi> tune her old Harp, now newly strung
to universal Harmony and Elegance, and rear
her awful Head from the stupid dismal Dozes
of Ages; where comes the literal Application
of my third Motto, <hi rend='smallcaps'>Renascimur</hi>.
</p>

<quote rend="display">
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Hinc priscæ redeunt Artes, felicibus inde
Ingeniis aperitur iter, despectaque Musæ
Colla levant.&mdash;&mdash;</foreign>
</quote>

<p>
Having travelled through a tedious Night,
thick-set with Horrors of various Hues! and
thus come to the End of a painful Journey;
give me Leave, kind Reader, to indulge awhile
with admiring the beautiful Variety of Objects,
which now surround me, to the serene Delight
<pb n='049'/><anchor id='Pg049'/>
of the Mind, and refined Gratification of Sense;
before I attempt that Display of them to which
I have no Occasion of professing my Inequality.
</p>

<p>
In this Reign, and not before, our Linen
Manufacture, in many Respects one of the most
profitable Branches of our national Commerce,
received all the Encouragement from Royal
Bounty, and Parliamentary Sanction, that could
be reasonably hoped for.
</p>

<p>
Persons of the highest Rank, Dignity, and
Fortune, were appointed <hi rend='italic'>Trustees</hi> for the Propagation,
Encouragement, and Diffusion, of this
beneficial Trade, throughout the respective Provinces.
</p>

<p>
The <hi rend='italic'>Linen-Hall</hi> was erected in <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>, under
as just and nice Regulations as any commercial
House in <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>.
</p>

<p>
The North of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> began to wear an Aspect
entirely new; and, from being (through
Want of Industry, Business, and Tillage) the
almost exhausted Nursery of our <hi rend='italic'>American</hi> Plantations,
soon became a populous Scene of Improvement,
Traffic, Wealth, and Plenty; and
is, at this Day, a well-planted District, considerable
for Numbers of well-affected, useful,
and industrious Subjects.
</p>

<p>
Now arose, now shone forth, the ever Honourable
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Dublin Society</hi>; a Society equalled
by none. It is true, we read of Patriarchs, Philosophers,
Warriors, Orators, and Poets; of
Senates, Parliaments, Councils, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi> but we no
where, abstracted from our own Country, meet
a Set of pious Patriots, from their <emph>private
Funds</emph>, adorning their Country in general, in
every Degree and Branch of Industry, and Improvement;
and, inspired with Sentiments truly
public and social, munificently rewarding their
<pb n='050'/><anchor id='Pg050'/>
Countrymen, of whatsoever Denomination, without
Favour or Distinction; for meliorating their
proper Estates, or Farms; for excelling in any
Production of Nature, or Art; for any Discovery,
or Invention, useful to Mankind: A Set
of <emph>truly honourable</emph>, and <emph>generous</emph> Personages, instructing
their Countrymen with clear, yet philosophical
Precepts, encouraging them by their
Example, and rewarding them from their inexhaustible
Bounty! <emph>Such</emph>, and <emph>such unrivalled</emph>,
is the <hi rend='smallcaps'>Illustrious Dublin Society</hi>! What
Pity, the ample Distributions, and instructive
Writings of this learned and munificent Body, are not regularly published,
in <hi rend='italic'>Latin</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>English</hi>,
and <hi rend='italic'>French</hi>, for the peculiar Honour of this
Nation, the Edification of Posterity, and as a
bright Pattern of Imitation to all other civiliz'd
Countries!
</p>

<p>
Now likewise appeared the <hi rend='italic'>Philharmonic Society</hi>,
that, (from a few Gentlemen, who used
<emph>occasionally</emph> to meet, in order to while away an
Hour with a gentle Tune, and chearful Glass)
grew into an harmonious Body, not alone for
the Improvement of the charming Art of Music,
but for the <emph>effectual Relief</emph> also of successive
Thousands, from Misery, Famine, and Confinement:
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Concordiâ res parvæ crescunt</foreign>.
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Orpheus</hi>,
we are told, built the Walls of <hi rend='italic'>Thebes</hi>,
by the irresistible Powers of Harmony: Be this
true or fabulous; how many Iron Gates have
we not seen open, to the persuasive Charities of
this tuneful Society! how many gloomy Cells
vacated by their Charms! This elegant Society,
by moderate Loans, Interest-free to the industrious
Poor, prevents many such from getting
into the Distress of Prisons, or following offensive
Courses; and, by enabling them to obtain
<pb n='051'/><anchor id='Pg051'/>
an honest Livelihood, rendereth them useful
Members to the Community: So that, of this
Society, it might have been justly said,
</p>

<lg>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Omne tulit Punctum quæ miscuit
utile dulci.</foreign></l>
</lg>

<p>
In this happy Reign was incorporated, under
the protective Sanction of Royal Bounty, a
Society, truly Christian, for the pious Establishment
of <hi rend='italic'>Protestant</hi> <hi rend='smallcaps'>Charter-Schools</hi>
throughout the Kingdom: An Institution far
more productive of national Morality, and Reformation,
than excommunicative Discipline, or
restrictive penal Statutes; since Persuasion and
Rewards have ever been, and must ever continue
to be, more consistent with the meek and benevolent
Temper of true Christianity, more effectual,
Apostolic, and Catholic, than <emph>Punishments</emph>,
<emph>Persecution</emph>, or <emph>Sequestrations</emph>.
</p>

<p>
In this Reign shines out a Christian Divine,
who, in the inestimable individual Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Madden</hi>,
collects <emph>a whole Society of Patriots</emph>; a venerable
Man, not alone the Guide of his particular
Congregation, but a pure, also clear and lasting
Light of Perfection, and noble Imitation, to
his Countrymen in general.
</p>

<lg>
<l>On <hi rend='italic'>Madden</hi>, kindred Angels smile!</l>
<l>Bright Mirrour to his native Isle!</l>
<l>To whom old Age shall say, and Youth,</l>
<l>With grateful and prophetic Truth,</l>
</lg>

<p>
<foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Semper Honos, Nomenq; tuum, Laudesq;
manebunt.</foreign>
</p>

<p>
St. <hi rend='italic'>Patrick's</hi> Hospital, for the Reception of
Lunaticks and Ideots, a lasting Monument of
the late Dean <hi rend='italic'>Swift's</hi> Charity, as are his various
<pb n='052'/><anchor id='Pg052'/>
Writings, of his great Genius and Wit: <hi rend='italic'>Mercer's</hi>
charitable Hospitable in <hi rend='italic'>Stephen-street</hi>: The
noble Hospital for the Relief of poor Lying-inn-Women,
of the Projection of our late excellent
Countryman, Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Bartholomew Mosse</hi>;
by which a great Number of Women and Children
are preserved from miserable and untimely
Ends: The <hi rend='italic'>Charitable Infirmary</hi> on the
<hi rend='italic'>Inns-Quay</hi>: The New Hospital for <hi rend='italic'>Incurables</hi>,
on <hi rend='italic'>Lazer's-Hill</hi>:
St. <hi rend='italic'>Nicholas's</hi> Hospital, in <hi rend='italic'>Francis-street</hi>:
The <hi rend='italic'>Meath</hi> Hospital, in <hi rend='italic'>Skinner's Alley</hi>:
The <hi rend='italic'>Lock</hi> Hospital, in <hi rend='italic'>George's-Lane</hi>,
for hapless Women and Children, tainted with the Venereal
Infection: And the Charitable Hospital in <hi rend='italic'>King-street,
Oxmantown</hi>, are all the humane and pious
Growth of this transcendent Reign.
</p>

<p>
Those Hospitals are duly and regularly attended,
by the most eminent Physicians, and
skilful Surgeons, without Fee or Reward: So
that, from this obvious Consideration, the frequent
and large Collections in our Churches, for
the comfortable Support, and Christian Education,
of indigent Boys; the stated Distributions
of our Chief Magistrates, to the Helpless and
Needy; and, in Truth, from the general Disposition
of its worthy Inhabitants; we may,
without any Risque of incurring the least Censure
of Adulation, or Vanity, pronounce <hi rend='smallcaps'>Dublin</hi>
as charitable a Metropolis as any in the known
World. In the beautiful new Garden, plann'd
by Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Mosse</hi>, breathing in all the natural Fragrance
of the Spring, adorned with all the Elegancies
of Art, all the Splendor of Illumination,
and inspired with the most soothing
Charms of delightful Harmony; to behold
Crowds of young Ladies, in the full Glow of
Beauty, and Bloom of Youth, finely habited,
<pb n='053'/><anchor id='Pg053'/>
and elegantly decorated in the Manufactures of
our own Country, (and finished in the most exquisite
Taste, by our own Artizans); to behold
them, I say, converting their very Amusements
and Recreations to the heavenly Purposes of relieving
the Distressed, must, to every thinking
<hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Spectator, afford a Prospect of the utmost
rational Joy!
</p>

<p>
As all Men, who render their Country distinguished
Honour, or singular Service, deserve,
therefore, lasting Monuments of public grateful
Acknowledgment to their Memories; it is
hoped that, in this Respect, Dr. <hi rend='italic'>Mosse</hi> will not
be forgotten by those who are evidently fond of
encouraging and rewarding public Zeal:
</p>

<lg>
<l>Eternal Joys to <hi rend='italic'>Mosse</hi> kind Heaven give,</l>
<l>By whom, on Earth, so many Thousands live!</l>
</lg>

<p>
The <hi rend='italic'>Marine Society</hi>, of recent Institution also,
disposeth many poor young Men into a Condition
of acquiring an honest, and praise-worthy
Livelihood, and of becoming useful Members
of the Community; by serving on Board of his
Majesty's Fleets in War-time, and serving our
Merchants in Times of Peace; and, in this
double Capacity, of contributing to the general
Welfare of their Mother-Country, to which
they may otherwise prove a Burden.
</p>

<p>
Our publick Entertainments of various Kinds
are, for the most Part, conducted with strict
Propriety, and real Politeness; those especially
of the Theatre, which should, by no Means,
pass for Matter of slight or casual Consideration;
seeing the <hi rend='italic'>Romans</hi>, the greatest of all People,
esteemed the Theatre worthy the Attention of
particular Laws, <hi rend='italic'>Roscia Lex Theatralis</hi>, &amp;c. Mr.
<pb n='054'/><anchor id='Pg054'/>
<hi rend='italic'>Sheridan</hi>'s general Merit as a <hi rend='italic'>Player</hi>
stands confessed; but as a <hi rend='italic'>Manager</hi>, that Gentleman's falling
frequently under the heavy Displeasure of
the Public, (whether from an haughty Distaste
to his Profession, or indulged Arrogance of
Temper) with his violent Introduction of anti-dramatick
Rope and Wire-dancing, Tumbling,
and Fire-eating, to the visible Degradation of a
liberal Stage, whereon nothing mean, shocking,
or monstrous, should ever appear; he hath not
succeeded so well: Then, his Scheme of uniting
an Academy, for the sober regular Education
of Youth, with a publick Theatre, seemed
rather the feverish Delusion of a distempered
Brain, and heated Imagination, than the cool
deliberate Result of rational Judgment; from
which fermented Source, also seem'd directly to
flow his avowed Concern for the <emph>long lost Art of
Oratory</emph> among us: Had Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Sheridan</hi> attended
to the Debates of our High Court of Parliament;
been frequent in our different Churches,
and at the Bars of our Courts of Judicature;
and had, in this Case, formed a comparative
Judgment, from the Writings of <hi rend='italic'>Demosthenes</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Plato</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Isocrates</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Cicero</hi>, and <hi rend='italic'>Pliny</hi> the Younger;
from the Rules and Precepts of <hi rend='italic'>Aristotle</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Longinus</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Horace</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Quinctilian</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Scaliger</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Rapin</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Porée</hi>,
and <hi rend='italic'>Rollin</hi>; he had been <emph>then</emph> convinced how
little Occasion there was for his <emph>lamenting</emph> the
<emph>Loss</emph> of an Art in this Kingdom, which breathes
there in full Maturity of all it's persuasive
Charms. This his dogmatical Assertion of the
<emph>long-lost Art of Oratory</emph>, his wild <emph>Academical</emph> Projects,
with the foregoing theatrical Inconsistencies,
too much subject that Gentleman to the
Character given, by the <hi rend='italic'>Roman</hi> Satirist, of an
assuming sharp-set <hi rend='italic'>Greekling</hi>:
</p>

<pb n='055'/><anchor id='Pg055'/>

<quote rend="display">
<hi rend='italic'>Gramaticus, Rhetor, Geometres, Pictor, Aliptes,
Augur, Scœnobates, Medicus, Magus, omnia novit.</hi>
</quote>

<p>
Upon the Whole, I will readily grant Mr.
<hi rend='italic'>Sheridan</hi> a <hi rend='italic'>Roscius</hi>, if the Name can sooth
him; a <emph>Critic</emph>; nay, an <emph>Orator</emph>; but I shall be bold
to assert, that we have many, very many, in
this Kingdom, of far greater Powers than that
Gentleman, whereof some of his Orations, <emph>so
called</emph>, are incontrovertible Testimonies.
</p>

<p>
This Kingdom hath of late Years exhibited
as justly celebrated Male and Female Players,
as any other; evinced in the Characters of
Messieurs <hi rend='italic'>Quin</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Ryan</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Delane</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Sheridan</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Barry</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Mossop</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Dexter</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Sparks</hi>, Mrs.
<hi rend='italic'>Woffington</hi>, the
inimitable Mrs. <hi rend='italic'>Fitz-Henry</hi>, and several others,
of either Sex.
</p>

<p>
Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Barry</hi>'s Capacity, as a Manager, appeareth
equal to his eminently-affecting Powers
in Tragedy, (so generally known, and so unexceptionably
confessed) from the magnificent
Theatre, erected by that Gentleman, with amazing
Expedition, in Grandeur, Convenience,
and Elegance, preferable to any in <hi rend='italic'>London</hi>, or
<hi rend='italic'>Paris</hi>: From the obliging Decency the respective
Performances thereof are conducted with, and
evidently from the surpassing theatrical Abilities
of the Company, that, with the most engaging
Variety, entertains the Publick in <hi rend='italic'>Crow-street</hi>
Play-house. I have sometimes seen, and have
been as often delighted, with Performances of
the Gentlemen just mentioned, as with those of
the admired Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Garrick</hi>, and the famous Messieurs
<hi rend='italic'>Dufrésne</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Gossin</hi>, and
<hi rend='italic'>Quinault</hi>; and, if I
may take Leave to declare my Opinion, am
therein clear that Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Barry</hi>, in the exquisitely
<pb n='056'/><anchor id='Pg056'/>
pathetick Strokes of deep Tragedy, touches the
Soul with as much delicate Sensibility, and, in
the irrefrainable Sallies of the more boisterous
Passions, soars with as majestick Wings, as any
one of them, I will not say higher. To behold
Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Barry</hi>, sublimely struggling in a Storm of
Adversity, with the sudden Shocks, and unexpected
Blows of Fortune; <emph>then</emph>, (when all human
Efforts must yield to inevitable Necessity)
sinking in the irretrievable Plunge of Sorrow
and Calamities, with that calm Resignation ever
attendant on true Heroism; must convince any
judicious Spectator of his being born a Tragedian.
I must here declare, that what I have
advanced on this Subject neither ariseth from
Prepossession on one Side, or Prejudice on the
other; having no Manner of Connection, nay,
not even a personal Acquaintance, with Mr.
<hi rend='italic'>Barry</hi>; nor any Objection to Mr. <hi rend='italic'>Sheridan</hi>,
but such as must naturally issue from my just Resentment
against any Individual, of whatsoever
Rank, Character, or Denomination, who should
prove so ignorant, and yet so hardy, as to declare
<hi rend='italic'>Elocution lost</hi> in our native Country; an illiberal
Censure, which, if true, had necessarily wrapped
our High Court of Parliament, the whole Body
of our Clergy, our University, Bench and Bar,
in Shades that, I am certain, had been never
dispell'd by the Approach of Light, so dim and
glimmering as that Gentleman's.
</p>

<p>
Let us now take a summary View of the Inhabitants
of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, in their respective Ranks:
And to begin with the Peers: Are they not such
Personages, as, by their Munificence, Affability
of Manners, Easiness of Comportment,
Propriety of Appearance, and Generosity in
dealing, reflect true Honour on Nobility; and,
<pb n='057'/><anchor id='Pg057'/>
Reality, derive their superior Rank, as much
from the Pre-eminence of their Virtues, as from
the constitutional Dignity of their Titles?
</p>

<p>
The Encrease of our People, Wealth, Commerce,
Industry, Arts, Inventions; the extraordinary
additional Number, in this happy
Reign, of our beautiful Seats, elegant Improvements,
useful and ornamental Plantations, extensive
Inclosures, excellent high Roads, (formerly
almost impassable,) with the visible Reformation
in national Harmony, and Allegiance,
will best suggest an Idea of the Honourable the
House of Commons of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, composed of
such candid Spirits, as, neither the Smiles or
Frowns of superior Influence, popular Views,
or private Connections, can bend from the various
essential Duties due to their King, their
Country, and themselves; constant in their
Attendance; careful in their Protection; and
zealous in their Promotion of publick Felicity;
not more extensive in their noble Projects, for
this great Purpose, than expeditious in carrying
those into Execution.
</p>

<p>
Our Constitution, partly of <hi rend='italic'>Gothic</hi>, partly of
<hi rend='italic'>Norman</hi> Institution, (the first High Court of
Parliament on the present Establishment, having
been ordained in the Reign of <hi rend='italic'>Henry</hi> the First,
Son of <hi rend='italic'>William</hi> the Conquerer) avoiding the
turbulent Licentiousness of a <hi rend='italic'>Democracy</hi>, the
factious domineering Temper of <hi rend='italic'>Aristocracy</hi>, and
the variable oppressive Sway of <hi rend='italic'>Arbitrary Monarchy</hi>;
but including, by an harmonious Assemblage,
the essential Virtues of those different
Systems of Government; is unquestionably the
<emph>best digested</emph> and <emph>wisest</emph> in the known World:
Under which, the King and the Nobles, with
the Commons, <emph>unite</emph>, to extend the Commerce,
<pb n='058'/><anchor id='Pg058'/>
promote the Happiness, guard over the Safety,
preserve the Lives, defend the Characters, support
the Liberties, and protect the Property of
the People. Bless'd Constitution! O! may it
ever flourish! under whose mild and preservative
Influence, a few only feel Restraint; except
from the Commission of private Evil, or
social Injury.
</p>

<p>
I have said a <emph>Few only</emph>; because there are some
among us, who, on the Score of Religion, are
secluded from permanent Property: And even
Those, it is hoped, will, in Consideration of the
invariable Tenor of their humble and pacific
Conduct, from the Capitulation of <hi rend='italic'>Limerick</hi>, to
this Day; and from their unanimous and chearful
Obedience to our Civil Government, e're
long obtain some Mitigation of their Affairs;
such the benevolent Temper and Disposition of
the present incomparable Reign! Some late
excellent<note place='foot'><hi rend='italic'>Seasonable Thoughts</hi>, &amp;c.
published by <hi rend='italic'>George Faulkner</hi>; <hi rend='italic'>the Case of
the Roman Catholics</hi>, and <hi rend='italic'>the Principles of the
Roman Catholics</hi>, the two last published by <hi rend='italic'>P. Lord</hi>, in
<hi rend='italic'>Cook-street, Dublin</hi>.</note>
Pamphlets, wherein these Gentlemen's
political Principles are fully and clearly explained,
shew of what signal Advantage it had been
to the Numbers, Industry, Health, Wealth,
and Beauty of this Kingdom, to indulge them
a Property, even in our uncultivated Mountains,
dreary Wastes, and noxious Marshes:
Which Measure, should it appear in a true Light
to our worthy Representatives, we may in a
few Years more, hope to see <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> one of the
most beautiful, best-improved, best-conditioned
Islands in the Universe. Our Bench is adorned
with Honourable Personages, conspicuous for
Learning, Integrity, Humanity, and Impartiality;
<pb n='059'/><anchor id='Pg059'/>
of whom, it may be boldly affirmed,
and with the strictest Truth, that they are not
Favourers of Persons. The present Lord Chief
Justice of the <hi rend='italic'>King-Bench</hi>, the late Master of
the Rolls, and Chancellor of the Exchequer,
Natives of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, formed a Triumvirate, whose
Learning, Worth, and distinguished Abilities,
had rendered them eminently respectable in the
brightest Æras, either of the <hi rend='italic'>Roman</hi> Commonwealth,
or Empire.
</p>

<p>
Our Attorney and Solicitor General, our Serjeants
at Law, and King's Council, with many
eminent Barristers, and a Set of learned eloquent
young Gentlemen, all shining out together;
such as <hi rend='italic'>Tully</hi>, <hi rend='italic'>Hortensius</hi>, and
<hi rend='italic'>Pliny</hi>, had with
fond Tenderness cherished and with pleasing
Pride, avowed for their Pupils; form as distinguished
a Body of Advocates and Orators, as
adorn any Courts of Judicature in <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>.
</p>

<p>
In the Diocese of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi> existeth a truly
pious Society for the Relief and Support of the
Widows and Children of the inferior Clergy
thereof. It is, indeed, surprizing in a Kingdom,
such (thank Heaven) as <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> is, that
the Example of this charitable Society, hath
not been <emph>universally</emph> followed. It hath often
affected me to the Quick, to have seen a learned
Divine, after a tedious and painful Free-School
Institution, and expensive University Education,
struggling, upon a poor Pension or Salary of
<emph>Forty</emph> Pounds a Year, to maintain an honest
Gentlewoman, Children, and Servants, (and
really with some Decency of Hospitality) sedulously
discharging, at the same Time, the different
Duties of the pastoral Function; when a
<emph>foreign Fidler</emph> shall run away with tripple that
Sum, or more, for one Night's Performance.
<pb n='060'/><anchor id='Pg060'/>
I would by no Means be understood to derogate
from the Merits of fine Performers in the different
Parts of Musick, or endeavour to diminish
their reasonable Perquisites: But, surely,
such Men and such Things are not to be thought
of, in Competition with those, who, by Teaching
and Preaching, refine our Morals, instruct
our Understandings, inform our Lives, and enlighten
our Souls with the celestial Spirit of the
Christian Faith; and thereby happily lead us,
through this transient and precarious State, to
eternal Tranquilly and Bliss. I am not a
Preacher; but thus far shall venture: As the
Fear of the Lord is the Beginning of Wisdom,
our generally following the heavenly Example
of this venerable Society, must be a great Test
as well of the one, as the other. If the Bishops,
the temporal Lords, and great estated Men of
each Diocese, would but graciously lead the
Way, it is not unlikely they had been attended
by Crowds of zealous Followers: And, in Fact,
a <emph>small</emph> Matter <emph>annually set apart</emph>, from even the
superfluous Outgoings of the Wealthy and
Opulent, of different Ranks, would very happily
answer the generous noble End of preserving,
from an anxious State of particular Dependance,
Numbers of virtuous, well-educated
Gentlewomen, and their Children, from the various
Miseries, which the untimely Death of a
Father, and narrow Circumstances, but too frequently
expose them to; an End so every Way
worthy the natural Disposition, the benevolent
Temper, the inherent Hospitality, and the essentially-charitable
Character of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<p>
Our <hi rend='italic'>Protestant</hi> Brethren, the <hi rend='italic'>Dissenters</hi>,
by a prudent and pious Regulation of secreting one
Pound a Year, each parochial Minister, for this
<pb n='061'/><anchor id='Pg061'/>
religiously humane Purpose, have constantly a
Fund sufficient to allow the Relict of each
Clergyman twenty Pounds a Year, (which preserves
her from the Miseries of Want and Dependance)
and have, at some Periods, where-with
to set their Children up, in an honest and
creditable Way of living. As we are emulously
fond of adopting the Wisdom and Virtues of
each Christian Sect and Society, it is fervently
hoped we will also this tender and pious Scheme;
a Scheme so comprehensive of true Charity, and
so productive of social and happy Effects! How
difficult is it for Minds, crowded with Cares,
and beset with the pressing Calls of Family-preservation,
to attend, with due Composure and
Inclination, to the various indispensible Duties
of the pastoral Office? But how chearfully would
those Reverend Gentlemen proceed in their
divine Mission, when, by some visible Provision
for the proper Objects of their present Cares and
future Concern, they should, in a great Measure,
be released from domestick Anxiety, from
gloomy Apprehensions, and alarming Prospects,
into the temporal Futurity of those, for whom
they must be necessarily affected with the most
tender Feelings!
</p>

<p>
The most convincing and decisive Method of
adjudging Causes, being by a comprehensive
View and critical Examination of their Effects;
of Streams, by a nice Scrutiny and Investigation
of their Sources; hence may we, from the
shining Characters, and extensive Abilities of
our Divines and Barristers, frame a just Idea of
the University of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>, which, for Compass
and Extent of the Sciences, Variety of elegant
Arts, found Erudition, and polite Literature
therein taught, in the most regular and perspicuous
<pb n='062'/><anchor id='Pg062'/>
Methods, is equalled by few, excelled by
none.
</p>

<p>
The Students are carefully instructed in the
more refined Parts of classical Learning; oriental,
antient, and modern Languages; Criticism,
sacred and profane History, Oratory, Logick,
Ethicks, and Metaphysicks; in natural and experimental
Philosophy; Anatomy, Botany and
Chymistry; the mathematicks, in Theory and
Practice; Civil and Canon Laws; Theology,
Controversy, and Ecclesiastical History: So
that, with a good Capacity, and regular Application,
one may depart this University, as
completely and happily instituted for the honorary
Professions of Life, as may be reasonably
expected from any Nursery of Learning extant.
The obtaining a Fellowship in this University,
is a demonstrative Test of comprehensive native
Talents, thorough intellectual Cultivation,
deep and various learned Acquirements.
</p>

<p>
The <hi rend='italic'>Newtonian</hi> Philosophy, the excellent
<hi rend='italic'>Boyle</hi>'s experimental Philosophy, and Mr.
<hi rend='italic'>Locke</hi>'s Metaphysicks,
prevail much in the College of <hi rend='italic'>Dublin</hi>:
Which, for Extent, Convenience, Magnificence,
and a most sumptuous elegant Library,
exceeds any one College in <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>. The beautiful
Parks belonging to it, seem actually, on a
serene Evening, the delightful Vale of <hi rend='italic'>Tempe</hi>,
or enchanting Recesses of <hi rend='italic'>Parnassus</hi>, inhabited
by all the Muses, all the Graces, with their
charming Train.
</p>

<p>
The Trade of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, however in former
Times miserably restrained and limited, hath in
this happy Reign received considerable Enlargements;
such as, the opening several Wooll-Ports;
the Bounty on <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Linens, now our
staple Commodity, imported into <hi rend='italic'>Great-Britain</hi>;
<pb n='063'/><anchor id='Pg063'/>
and the Immunity lately granted of importing
thither Beef, Butter, Tallow, Candles, Pork,
Hides, live Cattle, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi> a Privilege that, in its
Consequences, must prove of signal Advantage
to both Nations; to <emph>this</emph> especially, as we shall
hereby be enabled, upon any occasional Exigency,
to supply our protecting Friends, and proportionably
stint the Hands of our Enemies,
who, (by the Profusion of Wines and spirituous
Liquors, annually exported from <hi rend='italic'>France</hi> to
Ireland, in Exchange for our Beef, Butter, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi>
to pass over the Gluts of Teas and Spirits, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi>
smuggled thence by the <emph>western</emph> Runners) have
constantly the Balance on their Side. Our Exports,
with those already mentioned, consist in
a few Cheeses, Salmon and Kelp: But, as our
Linens are, without Question, become the vital
Spring of <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Commerce, it is Matter of great
Concern and equal Surprize, that the other Provinces
do not more <emph>universally</emph> and <emph>effectually</emph> follow
the lucrative Example of the <hi rend='italic'>North</hi>! since,
it is evident, nothing but <emph>equal Industry</emph> can be
wanting to render them <emph>equally flourishing</emph>, The
Over-growth of Graziers and Stockmasters, is
the strongest Indication that can be of national
Waste and Decay, in respect of Inhabitants.
What could a Foreigner, travelling among us,
particularly in the <emph>western</emph> Counties, some Summers
past, judge of our national Wisdom and
Oeconomy? Would he not start even at our
Humanity, on seeing the best arable Grounds
in the Kingdom, in immense Tracts, wantonly
enjoyed by the Cattle of a few petulant Individuals;
and at the same Juncture, our high
Ways and Streets crowded with Shoals of mendicant
fellow-creatures! reduced, through Want
of proper Sustenance, to the utmost Distress?
<pb n='064'/><anchor id='Pg064'/>
Would not a <hi rend='italic'>Frenchman</hi> for Example, give a
Shrug extraordinary, at finding, in every little
Inn, <hi rend='italic'>Bourdeaux</hi> Claret and <hi rend='italic'>Nantz</hi> Brandy,
though, in all Likelihood, not a Morsel of <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi>
Bread?
</p>

<p>
It is much to be hoped, That, when the Spirit
of Tillage should become more general and
active, our Farmers more attentive to the
Growth of the best Kinds of Grain, and our
Brewers, more attentive to the Rules and Precepts
for that Purpose laid down by the Honourable
the <hi rend='smallcaps'>Dublin Society</hi>; we shall have
little or no Occasion for that Inundation of <hi rend='italic'>London
Porter</hi>; (an heavy, cloudy, intoxicating,
ill-flavoured Liquor) that annually overflows
this City and other Parts of the Kingdom; as,
in the above Case, we may have a sufficient
Plenty and Variety of Malt Liquors, our own
native Produce, far better than any imported;
and, in Case of a Redundancy of Grain, (a
Matter not very likely to happen) may, with
moderate Care, have Spirituous Liquors of far
a more wholesome Nature, exquisite Taste, and
delicate Flavour, than those imported at an extraordinary
Expence; and but too often adulterated,
in the first Concoction.
</p>

<p>
We have, in several Parts of this Kingdom,
(in the Province of <hi rend='italic'>Munster</hi> especially) a recy,
spirituous, fine-flavoured Cyder, very little, if
at all, inferior to the best imported White
Wines; and a moderate Plenty of grateful
Honey-Liquors, which, with our prime Beef,
Mutton, Pork, Veal, Lamb, Variety of Fowls,
tame and wild; red and fallow Deer; Hares,
Rabbits, Pidgeons, Pheasants, Grouse; and
Partridge; wild Duck, Plover, Snipe, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi>
Lake, River, Shell and Sea Fish, of all Kinds;
<pb n='065'/><anchor id='Pg065'/>
the Produce of the Garden, (Horticulture having
of late Years so vastly improved among us,
that we now have many curious Plants, Fruits,
and Flowers, not only not <emph>known</emph>, but never
even <emph>heard of</emph>, in former Times) and <emph>all</emph> in such
Plenty and Perfection, as demonstrate <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>
happier than most other Countries, in regard
of the Necessaries and even of the Delicacies of
Life; to which may be added, the great Number
of our beautiful Lakes, noble Rivers, pure
Fountains, limpid Streams, and Health-restoring
mineral Wells.<note place='foot'>To all the above Productions of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, may be justly
added, our inestimable Fisheries, and plentiful Mines, which,
under due national Encouragement, would raise immense
Treasures.</note> In this Country are bred
valuable Horses, for the Draught, Road, and
Chace; and for the Course, as high-formed
ones, as in any Part of <hi rend='italic'>Europe</hi>; and large horned
Cattle, and Sheep in Abundance.
</p>

<p>
It must afford real Satisfaction to consider the
universal and visible Reformation in the Lives
and Morals even of our common People, clearly
evinced in this, that (thank Heaven) fewer
legal Punishments succeed an entire Circuit, in our
happy Days, than did a single Assize in former
Reigns: And, without Question, this Reformation
must still rise higher, in Proportion to the
Lenity of our worthy Legislature, and wise Indulgence
of our landed Men, who must certainly
find it more conducive to the Welfare of the
State, and to their own Strength, Honour, and
Interest, to have their Estates farmed and inhabited
by a great Number of honest, laborious
improving Families, than wasted by a few Purse-proud
Bullock-Brokers, who rarely allow the
wretched Herd of an hundred, as much Ground
<pb n='066'/><anchor id='Pg066'/>
for his own and poor Family's Support, as is
equal to that of two Bullocks.
</p>

<p>
Suppose a Gentleman was to let two thousand
Acres of arable Ground to farm; were it not
demonstrably more conducive to all the foregoing
Motives, to dispose of these to twenty honest,
industrious Families, at an hundred Acres each,
than to any one Beau-Grazier whatever? From
the twenty Tenures, the Landlord may, in any
national Shock, raise a considerable Number of
effective Hands, and zealous Hearts, for the
Service of the Crown, or Defence of his Country;
and reap many signal Advantages to the
public and private Concernments of Life, not
possibly derivable from the anti-social Monopolizers
and Forestallers of Farms; who ever fondly
attribute their Growth to their own Sagacity
and Cleverness, without any the least Gratitude
or Obligation to the Land-owner. These Sentiments,
it is hoped, will every Day gain more
and more Consideration with our wise and beneficent
Legislature, Nobility and Gentry.
</p>

<p>
Many intelligent Persons, of all Ranks, complain
much of the Want of some Establishment
in the Way of a national Bank, to secure popular
Credit, and the Kingdom from the various
alarming Shocks it is so frequently incident to,
on Account of the Failure of particular Banks.
</p>

<p>
The Nobility and Gentry of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, are
Loyalists and Patriots by Principle and Education:
They are brave, without Arrogance; gay,
without Levity; polite, without Affectation;
charitable, without Ostentation; religious, without
Formality; affable, without Meanness;
generous, without View; and hospitable, without
Reserve: In their Converse, easy; in their
Dealings just; placable in their Resentments, in
<pb n='067'/><anchor id='Pg067'/>
their Friendship steady:&mdash;They have neither
the volatile Airyness of the <hi rend='italic'>Frenchman</hi>, the stated
Gravity of the <hi rend='italic'>Spaniard</hi>; the supicious Jealousy
of the <hi rend='italic'>Italian</hi>; the forbidding Haughtiness of
the <hi rend='italic'>German</hi>; the saturnine Gloominess of the
<hi rend='italic'>Flandrican</hi>, nor the sordid Parsimony of the
<hi rend='italic'>Dutchman</hi>: In short, they are neither whimsical,
splenetic, sullen or capricious:&mdash;And, as for
Cunning, Craft, or Dissimulation, these are such
sorry Guests as never found Shelter in the generous
Breast of an <hi rend='italic'>Irish</hi> Noble or Gentleman; so
that, if we consider this Country, with regard
to its military Fame, constitutional Wisdom,
Learning, Arts, Improvements, and natural
Advantages; and above all, the benevolent
Temper, charitable and hospitable Disposition
of its Inhabitants; it is true, we may find many
of more popular Bustle and Eclat, more extensive
Commerce, greater Opulence and Pomp;
but none of more general, solid, and intrinsick
Worth, than <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<p>
I shall conclude with the following Proposition
to any one, who may arrogate to himself
Praise or Wit, by ridiculing <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.
</p>

<lg>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Si quid Novisti rectius
istis&mdash;</foreign></l>
<l><foreign lang="la" rend='font-style: italic'>Candidus imperti; Si non, his utere
mecum.</foreign></l>
</lg>

</div>

<pb n='068'/><anchor id='Pg068'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>The Farmer's Case Of The Roman-Catholics Of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>.</head>

<p>
In a <hi rend='smallcaps'>Letter</hi> from a <hi rend='smallcaps'>Member</hi> of the
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Protestant Church</hi>.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='smallcaps'>Dear Sir</hi>,
</p>

<p>
I think myself indebted to any Occasion
that restores you to a Friend,
whom I feared you had long forgotten.
But I confess, at the same
Time, that the Pleasure of hearing
from you, after a Silence of Several Years, is,
in some Measure, damped by the Censure that
seems to constitute the chief Intent of your
Letter.
</p>

<pb n='069'/><anchor id='Pg069'/>

<p>
You tell me that you lately happened upon
some Papers that were entitled The FARMER's
LETTERS, <hi rend='italic'>&amp;c.</hi> which were imputed to me
as the Author. And, after some Compliments
on Spirit, and Genius, and so forth, in order to
palliate, as I suppose, what you purpose to administer,
you charge me, by Implication, with
Crimes, whose smallest Tendency I should abhor
in myself, as in any Man breathing.
</p>

<p>
You say, favourably enough for your own
Disposition, that you have long looked on the
<hi rend='italic'>Roman-Catholics</hi> of these Kingdoms as a discountenanced
and pitiable People. That you
would choose to allow to others the same Latitude
of Conscience that you like for yourself.
That it is not a Part of Humanity to break a
Reed already bruised. That such a Treatment
would be blameable respecting any Individual;
how much more so, in Prejudice of a whole
People. That those Papers are pointed with a
Keenness of Enmity, for which the Talents,
which you are pleased to ascribe, cannot sufficiently
apologize. And, that you did not think
me capable of exasperating Government and
Power against a Set of Men who were already
under the Displeasure and Depression of the
Law.
</p>

<p>
These, my dear Friend, are home and heavy
Accusations, however tempered by Expressions
of Kindness and Affection from the Man whom
I sincerely love and respect.
</p>

<p>
But, if I know any-thing of myself, the Quality,
called Ill-nature, is not my Characteristic.
I would not exchange one Grain of Good-heart
for all the Wit of a <hi rend='italic'>C----d</hi> or Comprehension
of a <hi rend='italic'>P--tt</hi>, independent of their Virtue.
And I may say, with great Truth, that an Excess
<pb n='070'/><anchor id='Pg070'/>
of Humanity hath occasioned all the Misfortunes
and Distresses of my Life.
</p>

<p>
I most solemnly assure you, that when I wrote
those Letters I was in perfect Love and Charity
with every <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholic</hi> in the Kingdom of
<hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>. I knew that they were a depressed People.
I had long pitied them as such. I was
sensible that the Laws, under which they suffered,
had been enacted by our Ancestors, when
the Impressions of Hostility were fresh and
warm, and when Passion, if I may venture to
say so, co-operated, in some Measure, with
Utility and Reason. I will go a Step further.
I thought those Laws not severe enough to suppress
them as Enemies, nor yet sufficiently favourable
to attach them to us as Friends. They
were not so cruel as, wholly, to serve for quelling;
and yet they had a Poignancy that might
tend to provoke. And all this I imputed to the
Resentment that was blended with the Humanity
of our Ancestors. Their Humanity left to Papists
a Power of hurting, while their Resentment
abridged the Inducements that might engage
them to serve us.
</p>

<p>
Believe me, Sir, I never was of a cruel or
persecuting Disposition. I was grieved to see
the Discouragements under which the <hi rend='italic'>Roman
Catholics</hi> of this Kingdom laboured, but these
very Discouragements made me fear them the
more.
</p>

<p>
Previous to the Letters, which you censure so
warmly, a dangerous Rebellion had broken out
in <hi rend='italic'>Scotland</hi>, in consequence of a <hi rend='italic'>French</hi>
Invasion, that was headed by a Popish Pretender to the
Throne. Be pleased to remember, (if it is not
too mortifying a Recollection for a free-born
<hi rend='italic'>Briton</hi>) the Pannic into which all <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>
was
<pb n='071'/><anchor id='Pg071'/>
struck by a few <hi rend='italic'>Scotch</hi> Vassals, undisciplined, and
unactuated by any Motive of Liberty or Virtue,
save the Virtue of being attached to their
<hi rend='italic'>Laird</hi> or their <hi rend='italic'>Leader</hi>. Millions of
<hi rend='italic'>English</hi>, at
that Time, sunk in the Down of a long Peace,
and enervated by ministerial Corruption and Venality,
feared that a Handful of <hi rend='italic'>Highlanders</hi>
would win their Way to <hi rend='italic'>London</hi>, and, at one
Stroke, put a Period to the boasted Strength and
Grandeur of the <hi rend='italic'>British</hi> Constitution.
</p>

<p>
I was astonished at the Apprehensions that
<hi rend='italic'>England</hi> was under from so contemptible an Armament.
But I deemed the Case of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi> to
be highly alarming. The <hi rend='italic'>Roman-Catholics</hi>, at
that Time, outnumbered us Five to One. They
were disarmed, it is true, but I was not equally
sure that they had Reason to be reconciled. As
they were not admitted to realize their Fortune,
it consisted of ready Money, and that gave
ready Power. As they were not permitted to
purchase, or accept a Tenure of any valuable
Length, Loyalty, perhaps, might induce them
to fight for their King; but where was the Stake
to impel them to fight for a Country in which
they had no <hi rend='italic'>Inheritance</hi>? Without an Interest
in Lands, they had little to lose by any Change
of Estate. Without a Loan lodged with Government,
they had the less to lose by a Change of
Constitution.
</p>

<p>
I cannot conceive how <hi rend='italic'>Religion</hi>, or mere Difference
of Opinion, should prove a real Cause
of Quarrel among Men; though it often serves
as a <hi rend='italic'>Word of War</hi>, or a <hi rend='italic'>Term</hi> whereby to give
Notice for Onset. On the contrary, I had observed
that wherever People are united by <hi rend='italic'>Interest</hi>,
though of a thousand opposite Sects, Persuasions
<pb n='072'/><anchor id='Pg072'/>
and Professions, they never fail to join
in the Maintenance and Defence of <emph>common
Rights</emph>.
</p>

<p>
I, therefore, did not fear the <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholics</hi>,
as having a different <hi rend='italic'>Religion</hi>, but as having
an <hi rend='italic'>Interest</hi> that was different from the Interest
of <hi rend='italic'>Protestants</hi>. Were they a Compound of all
the Follies, Absurdities, and Contradictions that
ever were generated by Monster-bearing Superstition,
had their Interest bound them to us, I
should not have feared their <hi rend='italic'>Fealty</hi>.
</p>

<p>
But this was not the Case. The <hi rend='italic'>French</hi> Invasion
of <hi rend='italic'>Great Britain</hi> was headed by a Person
who was, by Birth, Education, Principle, and
Interest, an Enemy to the Freedom and Rights
of a Constitution that was established on the Dispossession
of his Ancestors; and he was, consequently,
an Enemy to the general Change of
Privilege and Property, that ensued on the said
Establishment. The said Change, as we all
know, was to the Disadvantage of <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholics</hi>.
Had the Invader prevailed, a Change
would again have ensued, in their Favour.
Men naturally with Success to an Event from
whence they propose Benefit; and it is as natural
for them to act conformable to those Wishes.
</p>

<p>
Had <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholics</hi> been possessed of an unrestrained
Property, along with the other Liberties,
Blessings, and Enjoyments, which they
derived, in common with us, from the Establishment
at the Revolution, no spiritual or
temporal Power on Earth could have tempted
them to permit, much less to wish, a Change
of a Constitution whose Equal they could not
find upon Earth.
</p>

<p>
But as this was very far from being the Fact,
I feared that <hi rend='italic'>Interest</hi> might prove an Incentive
<pb n='073'/><anchor id='Pg073'/>
to <emph>Desire</emph>; and Desire equally prove an Incentive
to <emph>Action</emph>; and, I am not ashamed to confess,
that my Expectations were greatly, though happily,
disappointed, by the Steadiness of their
peaceful and loyal Demeanour on that trying
Occasion.
</p>

<p>
Believe me, my Friend, at the Time that I
wrote those Papers, which have given you so
much Offence, I looked upon the <hi rend='italic'>Papists</hi> of this
Kingdom, by the Patronage of <hi rend='italic'>France</hi> and
<hi rend='italic'>Spain</hi>, by their Numbers, by their Wealth, and by
their Union with each other, to be vastly superior
to <hi rend='italic'>Irish Protestants</hi>, in Power; and my Spirit
of Opposition rose, in Proportion to my Idea
of their Ability. But neither then, before, nor
since, did I ever mean to excite any Action, or
Intention, against the Weak, or the Oppressed,
the Fallen, or the Afflicted.
</p>

<p>
When <hi rend='italic'>Brutus</hi> unsheathed the reluctant Sword
of Freedom against his Friend, Humanity must
suppose that his Heart was wrung with Compunction,
while his Country enjoined and impelled
the Blow.
</p>

<p>
But further, Sir, there is a very wide Difference
between a <hi rend='italic'>Popish Regency</hi> and a <hi rend='italic'>Popish
People</hi>. The whole Intent and Virulence, as
you call it, of my Papers, is pointed and levelled
against the <emph>One</emph>, but not a Syllable uttered,
from End to End, against the <emph>Other</emph>. A <hi rend='italic'>Popish
Regency</hi>, in Temporals alike as in Spirituals, I
held to be, by Principle, an arbitrary and oppressive
Government; but I held a <hi rend='italic'>Popish People</hi>
to be, of all People, the most amenable and
submissive to Rulers, whatever the Form or
Nature of that State may be, under which they
shall happen to be subjected. And, on this
very Account, I dreaded them the more, should
<pb n='074'/><anchor id='Pg074'/>
they become passive Instruments in the Hand of
a Papal Dictator.
</p>

<p>
To apply a sure Test to the Propriety, or Impropriety,
of my Apprehensions, at the Period
when I wrote the <hi rend='italic'>Farmer's Letters</hi>, let us suppose
that no one of the Penal Laws, which
were instituted during the Reign of her Majesty
Queen <hi rend='italic'>Anne</hi>, had yet passed into Form,
but that Matters had remained in the same Situation,
in which the <hi rend='italic'>Monarch</hi>, of <hi rend='italic'>humane</hi>, as well
as <hi rend='italic'>glorious Memory</hi>, had left this unhappy People.
Well, what would have been the Consequence?
Would <hi rend='italic'>Papists</hi>, in that Case, have
been less amenable to the Government, by
which they had been favoured, supported, and
cherished? Would they have been the forwarder
to bring Damage and Destruction on a Country,
because their own Interest was connected
therewith, and the Fortunes of their Posterity
deposited therein? Would they have been the
readier to attempt the Overthrow of our beneficent
Constitution, because they enjoyed the Privileges
and Advantages thereof? No, Sir, no.
The Absurdity of the Supposition is inclusive of
the Answer. Had this been the Case, the <hi rend='italic'>Farmer's
Letters</hi> would not have existed to have
caused the Renewal of our Acquaintance.
</p>

<p>
I have read and noted many Instances, in free
States and Commonwealths, where <hi rend='italic'>Liberty</hi>, when
fermented into <hi rend='italic'>Licentiousness</hi>, hath occasioned
many partial Struggles for Power, many Broils
and Factions, and much Disturbance to the
Community. But very few are the Instances of
the Insurrection of any People, who have not
been goaded thereto by Severity and Oppression.
The inoffensive Stag grows formidable when <hi rend='italic'>at
<pb n='075'/><anchor id='Pg075'/>
Bay</hi>. The Worm turneth not, till it receiveth
a Crush.
</p>

<p>
I forget the Book, though I remember the
Passage, where a Prince demanded of his favourite
Minister, what he should do with a
Number of the Commons and Nobility, whom
he had suppressed and taken Captive in the Act
of Rebellion? The Minister answered, <hi rend='italic'>Put
them, and their Adherents, instantly to Death</hi>. No,
replied the Prince, that were an Act of such
Bloodshed and Barbarity, as neither Fear nor
Revenge shall persuade me to perpetrate. <hi rend='italic'>Then,
grant them all free Pardon</hi>, rejoined the Minister.
How! said the Prince, must Rebellion
go altogether unpunished? There is no Medium
that can assure your Safety, answered the
Minister; you must either pull this Party wholly
up by the Root, so as to leave no Fibre from
whence future Enmity may grow; or else, you
must change that Enmity into Friendship, by
binding their Gratitude to your Person and Interest,
with the kindliest of all Connections,
that of your Goodness and Favour. <hi rend='italic'>A partial
Punishment will be too little for your Safety; a partial
Pardon will not be enough.</hi> You must either
wholly annihilate their Power, by their <hi rend='italic'>Death</hi>;
or derive Strength to yourself, from that Power,
by their <hi rend='italic'>Friendship</hi>.
</p>

<p>
By disarming our Enemies, the utmost we
can hope, is, to render them impotent. The
Diminution of <emph>their</emph> Power adds nothing to our
<emph>own</emph>. Repentance is never so permanent or sincere,
as when preceded by Pardon; and Favour
is, as the polar Attraction, to Inclination. Is
there a Man whose Love and Gratitude you
desire to engage? Common Sense will direct
you to do him a Benefit. Would you bind him
<pb n='076'/><anchor id='Pg076'/>
to your Service with Hoops of Steel? You
must make it his Interest, as well as his Duty,
to befriend you.
</p>

<p>
It is, by no means, my Intention to arraign
either the Wisdom or good Policy of our Forefathers.
But all Men are, in some Degree,
fallible, as well in the congregate, as in the individual;
and the Shrewd may err as much,
by over-reaching their Aim, as the Ignorant,
by falling short, or deviating from it.
</p>

<p>
But, had a hundred <hi rend='italic'>Pitts</hi>, and a hundred
<hi rend='italic'>Cecils</hi>, composed the Senate of our Ancestors, at
the Time that those <hi rend='italic'>Penal Laws</hi> were enacted;
had those Laws been ever so wise and so just,
so wholesome and necessary, and well suited to
the Season; is that a Reason that they should
<emph>continue so</emph> to the End of Time? In a World
where nothing is permanent; where Modes,
Manners, Principles, and Practice are at a Flux;
where Life is uncertain, and all it contains
changeable; Nature and Reason will conform to
Situation and Circumstance; and where <hi rend='italic'>Causes</hi>
have ceased, in any Degree, the <hi rend='italic'>Consequences</hi>
ought to cease in the same Proportion.
</p>

<p>
It is not now with <hi rend='italic'>Rome</hi> as it was in the Days
when Princes held her Steed, and Emperors
her Stirrup. The Kings of the Earth have,
pretty clearly, resumed her Usurpations and
Acquisitions of temporal Dominion. It is not
now, as it was when she cried Peace! and it became
Peace; or when the Breath of her Mandate
kindled the Nations to Battle. Even his
<hi rend='italic'>Holiness</hi> is, now, but a poor limited Prince, pent
up within his little <hi rend='italic'>Italian</hi> Demesne. If some few
still acknowledge to hold of his Authority, it
is a Homage of Words, and not of Facts;
they will not acknowledge to hold of his Power.
<pb n='077'/><anchor id='Pg077'/>
He is restored to the quiet and unenvied Possession
of all the Lordship and Interest he can acquire
in Heaven. But the Sceptre, even of his
spiritual Dominion upon Earth, is, of late, as
I take it, most wonderfully shortened.
</p>

<p>
Matters are much altered with the ecclesiastical
World, even since I wrote the Letters that
have roused your Spleen. Whether it be through
a Decline of the <hi rend='italic'>Romish</hi> Religion, in particular;
or, possibly, through a Decline of all Religion,
in general; the pontifical and episcopal Dictatorship
and Authority are wofully fallen, from the
Chair of Infallibility, where they had been seated
by Opinion. The Sons of the most bigotted
Ancestors do now perceive, that Piety and Immorality
are not rightly consistent. And even
the vulgar and ignorant, among the <hi rend='italic'>Roman</hi> Laity,
would grumble at departing from an Inch
of their Property, though the Priest should
advise, and the Pope, himself, should enjoin
it.
</p>

<p>
But, Sir, if the Change of Times, and Principles,
Situation, and Circumstances; if the
Change of every Cause that produced those
penal Laws, have not availed for a Change of
<hi rend='italic'>Consequences</hi>; for some Mitigation or Abatement
of their Rigour, toward these my unhappy Brethren,
the <hi rend='italic'>Roman Catholics of Ireland</hi>: If no
Argument, I say, that is taken from Changes,
may avail for the Purpose, I will take one from
Permanence and Duration itself, that shall strike
Light and Conviction to the Eye of every Beholder;
that Power may <emph>gainsay</emph>, but cannot
<emph>refute</emph>; that Malevolence may <emph>dispute</emph>, but never
can <emph>answer</emph>.
</p>

<p>
About six Generations have now passed away,
according to the Rates of Purchase and Estimate
<pb n='078'/><anchor id='Pg078'/>
of the Life of Man, since these People have offended
in Word or in Deed. No Riotings have
been heard in their Houses, no Complainings
in their Streets; they have been silent and harmless
as Sheep before their Sheerers. Our Parties,
Factions, and Insurrections, as they are merrily
stiled in <hi rend='italic'>England</hi>, have been all among ourselves;
this People were neither Actors nor
Partakers therein. They have offered themselves
to our Fleets, and to our Armies; to tend our
Persons, to till our Grounds, to hew our Wood,
and to draw our Water. Where we admit them
to fight for us, they have ever proved valiant;
where we admit them to serve us, they are found
loving, observant, and faithful. Temptations
have come to their Doors and called them forth;
the Contagion of Rebellion hath broken out
among their Neighbours; they have yet remained
quiet, and continued untainted; still
loyal to their Sovereign, amenable to Government,
and submissive to Law, through a long
and trying Succession of about seventy Years,
they have scarce appeared to repine in the midst
of their Calamities.
</p>

<p>
When I look back on the querulous and restless
Nature of Man: When I trace the human
Propensities through the Records of Ages and
Nations: In all the Histories of those States
who had least Cause of Complaint: Throughout
the Commonwealths of <hi rend='italic'>Asia Minor</hi>, the
<hi rend='italic'>Archipelago</hi>, the <hi rend='italic'>Grecian Continent</hi>,
<hi rend='italic'>Italy</hi>, the Islands
of the <hi rend='italic'>Mediterranean</hi>, &amp;c. where the RIGHTS
OF NATURE, under Forms of various Institution,
were ASSERTED BY LIBERTY AND
GUARDED BY LAW: Where the ASSURANCE
OF PROPERTY gave most REASON
FOR CONTENT: I can find but few
<pb n='079'/><anchor id='Pg079'/>
Instances of any People who, through such a
Length of Time, have continued firm and unshaken,
in an uninterrupted Loyalty and Submission
to Government.
</p>

<p>
What then, do we look for further? What
Proofs do ye yet require, of Peacefulness and
Attachment at the Hands of these our Brethren?
Is no Period to be put to their State
of Probation? Must they <emph>for ever</emph> keep out
upon <emph>Quarantine</emph>, without Harbour or Hopes
of Rest or Reconciliation? That were hard,
indeed.
</p>

<p>
If it is Revenge that we seek, they have,
already, suffered enough, not for their own
Faults, but for the Hostility of their Forefathers.
If we seek our Safety, alone; let us chace <emph>them,
at once, from Country and Community</emph>; or put
an <emph>End to our domestic Fears</emph>, by giving them
Cause to defend us.
</p>

<p>
Indeed, Sir, neither common Sense, nor Sense
of any Kind, can possibly suppose, That Acts
of Kindness which have been, from the Beginning
of the World, the Cement of Friendship
to all other People, should prove the reverse to
these People alone.
</p>

<p>
Had they been to us, as the Swallow, in Autumn,
who forsakes all Connections on the Approach
of Inclemency, I should never have
pleaded for any Confidence in them. But a People,
who, through a Winter of seventy Years
Continuance, have never failed, or forsaken, or
given us Cause of Offence, surely merit some
Consideration, some grateful and chearing Ray
to warm them to a Sense that <hi rend='italic'>Protestants</hi> are not,
by Choice, of a cruel, unforgiving, and malevolent
Nature.
</p>

<pb n='080'/><anchor id='Pg080'/>

<p>
Lastly, Sir, as I know you to be a Gentleman
of a communicative Disposition, and that you
were, formerly, fond of exhibiting the Sentiments
of some of your Friends; should you
impart this Letter to any of your popish Acquaintance,
I doubt they might be apt to give
me more Thanks than I am conscious I deserve.
It is, therefore, but commonly honest, to advertise
you, and them, that while I write in the
Favour of <hi rend='italic'>Papists</hi>, the Interest of
<hi rend='italic'>Protestants</hi> is
never out of my Eye.
</p>

<p>
When I thought your Favourites most formidable,
I shewed I did not fear them; and
now, that I think them impotent, let them not
think I flatter.
</p>

<p>
What I have hitherto hinted is but a narrow
opening to the Concerns and Interests of an
unhappy Country, whereof I have the Misfortune
to be a helpless, though loving, Member.
To promote the Advantage of <hi rend='italic'>Ireland</hi>, in any
respect, would be, to me, the cardinal Point
of the whole Compass of my Ambition; and
a subsequent Letter may shew how far my Observations
relate to the Decline, or Prosperity, of
my Country, whenever you confer the Pleasure
of an Answer on,
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Dear</hi> SIR,<lb/>
<hi rend='italic'>Your truly affectionate</hi>, &amp;c.
</p>

</div>

</body>
<back rend="page-break-before: right">
  <div id="footnotes">
    <index index="toc" />
    <index index="pdf" />
    <head>Footnotes</head>
    <divGen type="footnotes"/>
  </div>
  <div rend="page-break-before: right">
    <divGen type="pgfooter" />
  </div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
